科技圈的坏消息。
Bad news for the tech community.
职业倦怠是一个严重的问题。
Burnout at work is a major problem.
而 AI 可能会让本已不堪重负的员工问题雪上加霜。
And AI could add to this already overwhelmed employee problem.
与 AI 的蜜月期已经结束了。当人们被问到， |
The honeymoon period with AI is over. When people are asked, what,
你在害怕什么？
what are you afraid of?
担心被 AI 抢走工作其实排在倒数第二。
Losing my job to AI is actually second to last.
排在最前面的是：拿一样的钱却要做更多的活。
What we saw rise up to the top is the expectation to do more for the same pay.
我们做了这项调查，了解科技从业者当下的真实感受。
We did this survey on how people are feeling in tech right now.
职业倦怠正在显著加剧。
Burnout is increasing significantly.
乐观情绪在下降。局面从未如此疯狂。
Optimism is declining. It's never been crazier.
我们什么时候才能聊到这一期里乐观的部分？
When are we gonna get to the optimistic part of this, uh, of this episode?
一半的科技从业者感觉好极了，而另一半，
Half of the people in tech are feeling incredible and the other half,
她告诉我们，我的脑子在退化。
and she told us, my brain is rotting.
我的工作感觉更糟了。Elon 有一个很有意思的说法。
My work feels worse. Elon had this really interesting way of describing it.
如果我们此刻还活着，那我们肯定生活在一个模拟世界里，
We're definitely living in a simulation if we're alive right now
我们即将开始在太空中建造数据中心，而 AI 将会
when we're about to start building data centers in space and AI is going to be
变得和人类一样聪明，这告诉我们应该做些什么？
as smart as human, what does this tell us we should be doing?
如果我们无所不能，那我们正处在一场巨变的第二局。
If we can do anything, we're in the second inning of a massive shift.
没人知道它会如何收场。但你能做的只有把握当下。
No one knows how it will end. But all you can do is today.
我的嘉宾是 Noam Segal。我和 Noam 认识很久了。
My guest is Noam Siegel. Noam and I go a long ways back.
我们在 Airbnb 共事多年，他是我的研究搭档。
We worked together at Airbnb for many years where he was my research partner.
之后他先后在 Intercom、Twitter、Wealthfront，
Since then he went on to be a research leader at Intercom, Twitter, Wealthfront,
Meta、Zapier 和 Figma 担任研究负责人。
Meta Zapier and Figma.
Noam 真的太棒了。
GNOME is so amazing.
在过去几年里，
And over the past couple years,
我很幸运能和他合作过一系列研究项目，
I've been lucky to partner with him on a bunch of research projects,
其中最有雄心的就是这项科技从业者心态调查，
the most ambitious of which has been a tech worker sentiment survey,
我们计划每年都做一次。
which we plan to run every year.
这是我们第二次做，结果非常有意思。
This is the second time we've run it, and the results are so interesting.
我相信这是同类调查中规模最大的一次，
I believe this is the largest survey of its kind,
探究科技从业者对工作、AI、裁员、
looking at how people in tech feel about their jobs and AI and layoffs
职业倦怠以及职业前景的真实感受。
and burnout and the future of their careers.
内容非常丰富。这一期基本上就是围绕调查结果的一次对话。
There's so much in this. And basically this episode is a conversation about the results.
在对话的最后，
At the end of the conversation,
我们会给出一系列建议，告诉你可以怎么做，
we go through a bunch of advice on what you might do
如果你现在正陷入困境、不知道该怎么办的话。
if you are currently on the struggle bus and trying to figure out what to do.
我对这一期非常兴奋。我对这份报告也非常兴奋。
I'm so excited for this episode. I'm so excited for this report.
非常感谢 Noam 付出的努力，设计调查、执行调查、
A big thank you to Noam for doing the work to create the survey, run the survey,
分析调查，并撰写了我们会附上链接的那篇文章。
analyze the survey and write the post that we will link to.
真的非常出色。
It is so good.
在正式开始之前，别忘了去看看 Lenny's Productpass.com，
Before we get into it, do not forget to check out Lenny's Product pass.com for a
免费获得为期一年、全球最热门、最精心打造的 AI 产品，
free year of the hottest and most well crafted AI products in the world,
仅向 Lenny's newsletter 的订阅者独家开放。那么，
available exclusively to Lenny's newsletter subscribers. With that,
让我为你介绍 Noam Segal。
I bring you Noam Siegel.
Noam，非常感谢你能来，欢迎来到播客。
Noam, thank you so much for being here, and welcome to the podcast.
太感谢你了，Lenny。能来到这里是一次非常棒的体验。
Thank you so much, Lenny. It's such an incredible experience to be here.
谢谢你的邀请。
Thanks for having me.
是我的荣幸。其实我们已经共事很久了，
It's my pleasure. We've actually worked together for a long time
而知道这件事的人不多。
and no few people know this.
我在 Airbnb 的时候，你是我们团队的研究员，
We, you were the researcher on our team when I was at Airbnb,
那大概是 10 年前，十年前了。
it was like 10 years ago, a decade ago.
十年前。Lenny，变化太大了。变化太大了。变化太大了。
A decade ago. Lenny, so much has changed. So much has changed. So much has changed.
这正好引出我们今天要聊的话题，
Which is a great segue to what we're gonna be talking about today,
也就是我们做了这项调查，了解科技从业者当下的真实感受。
which is we did this survey on how people are feeling in tech right now.
局面从未如此疯狂。所以我们做了这份报告，就是想了解大家的真实感受。
It's never been crazier. And so we did this report on just how are people feeling.
这是我们第二次做了。一年前我们做过一次。
And this is the second time we've done this. We ran this a year ago.
我们的想法是，每年都做这项科技从业者心态调查，
And the idea here is we're gonna have this yearly tech sentiment survey
持续追踪科技从业者的真实感受。
that's gonna track how tech people are feeling.
在我们进入核心结论之前，
Before we get into the takeaways,
先给我们讲讲这项调查的背景，比如你是怎么做的？
what's kind of the give us a little context just on the survey, like how, how you ran it?
你都看了哪些方面？有什么大家需要知道的？对，说说你的观点。
How, what were you looking at? Anything people need to know? Yes, it's your point.
这是我们第二次做这项调查，
This is the second time we're running this survey,
我真心觉得它在科技行业里是独一无二的。
which I really feel is unique in the tech industry.
我很感激你给了我这个机会，也给了我们这个机会，
I appreciate you for giving me the opportunity and giving us an opportunity
让我们作为一个社区，更深入了解大家在科技行业里的真实感受。
as a community to learn more about how we're all feeling in tech.
我不知道有哪项调查能达到这样的规模，关注这些议题。
I'm not aware of any survey like this at this scale, looking at these things.
去年我们做类似的 Tech Sentiment 调查时，
Last year, when we ran the similar Tech Sentiment,
也就是首届 Tech Sentiment 调查，标题是「倦怠但乐观」。
the first inaugural Tech sentiment survey, the title was burnt out but optimistic.
我们看到相当高的职业倦怠水平，
We were seeing fairly high levels of burnout,
但对未来走向也有相当高的乐观情绪。
but also fairly good levels of optimism about where things are going.
我们其实针对倦怠这一点做了后续研究，还创建了 armor 框架，
And we actually followed up on the burnout point and we created the armor framework,
如果你还记得的话。
if you remember.
我真的很高兴今年我们做了这个。我们调查了大约 6,000 人。
And I'm, I'm really glad we, we did that this year. We surveyed about 6,000 people.
涵盖产品、工程、设计、研究、市场，几乎所有岗位，
From product engineering, design, research, pretty much any role, marketing,
几乎涵盖科技行业的所有岗位。
pretty much any role in tech.
结果非常有意思。所以我很兴奋要深入讲讲。
And the results were very interesting. So I'm very excited to jump into them.
是啊，我还记得你分享分析初稿的时候，
Yeah, I just remember when you shared the first draft of the analysis, uh,
我一边读一边想，天哪，这太有意思了。
as just like reading it, I was like, holy shit, this is so interesting.
感觉它把一些东西说出来了。
And it just feels like it's putting words to.
说出了我的感受，也说出了我听到很多人的感受。
The way I feel, the way that I hear a lot of people feel.
所以我真的很兴奋我们在做这件事。
So I'm really excited that we're doing this.
本期节目由我们本季的冠名赞助商 WorkOS 支持。
This episode is brought to you by our season's presenting sponsor, work OS.
OpenAI、Anthropic、Cursor、Vercel、Replit、
What do open AI? Anthropic Cursor, Versel Replit,
Sierra、Clay 以及数百家成功公司有什么共同点？
Sierra Clay and hundreds of other winning companies all have in common?
它们都由 WorkOS 提供支持。
They are all powered by work OS.
如果你在为企业客户打造产品，
If, if you're building a product for the enterprise,
你一定体会过集成单点登录的痛苦，
you've felt the pain of integrating single sign on,
还有 SCIM、RBAC、审计日志等大公司要求的功能。
skim RBAC audit logs and other features required by large companies.
WorkOS 把这些成交障碍变成即插即用的 API，配套一个现代开发者平台，
Workos turns those deal blockers into drop in APIs with a modern developer platform
专为 B2B SaaS 打造。
built specifically for b2b Saas.
说真的，我投资的每一家初创公司，
Literally, every startup that I'm an investor in
只要开始向高端市场扩张，最后都会用上 WorkOS。
that starts to expand upmarket ends up working with workos.
那是因为它们是最好的，
And that's because they are the best,
无论你是想拿下第一个企业客户的种子期初创公司，
whether you are a seed stage startup trying to land your first enterprise customer
还是正在全球扩张的独角兽。
or a unicorn expanding globally.
WorkOS 是达到企业级就绪、打通增长瓶颈的最快路径。
Workos is the fastest path to becoming enterprise ready and unblocking growth.
它本质上就是企业级功能领域的 Stripe。
It's essentially stripe for enterprise features.
访问 workos.com 即可开始，或者直接去他们的 Slack，
Visit workos com to get started or just hit up their slack
那里有真正的工程师等着回答你的问题。
where they have actual engineers waiting to answer your questions.
WorkOS 让你借助好用的 API、详尽的文档更快地开发，
Workos allows you to build faster with delightful APIs, comprehensive docs,
以及流畅的开发者体验。
and a smooth developer experience.
访问 workos.com，让你的应用达到企业级就绪。今天，
Go to work. os.com to make your app enterprise ready. Today,
我们要过一遍十大要点。
we're going to go through the top 10 takeaways.
整份报告的大局要点大概是什么，
What's kind of the, like, the big picture takeaway from the report overall,
如果只能带走一个最重要的结论的话？
if someone could take one big takeaway away?
首先我要说，你和我都注意到了 Elena Verner 的一篇很精彩的帖子，
Well, first I'll say that you and I both noticed an incredible post from Elena
就在这期播客录制前几天发的。
Verner a couple of days before this pod was recorded.
她谈到了「AI 信心表演」，
And she's talking about the AI confidence theater
以及如今科技圈的对话里，什么都「死了」。
and how in conversations these days in tech, everything is dead.
首先，工程编程死了，设计死了，SaaS 死了，等等。
First of all, engine coding is dead, design is dead, SAS is dead, etcetera.
显然，这不是事实。
Obviously, that's not true.
所以你即将在这些结果里看到的，是我们能提供的最好的图景，
So what you're about to see in these results is the best picture we could provide
也可能是迄今为止任何人提供过的
and probably the best picture anyone's provided
关于人们对 AI 真实感受的最好图景。
so far of how people are really feeling about AI.
在我看来，这也关联到一点：如果你，
And to me, this also ties to the fact that if you were,
如果你在看这期节目、又在科技行业工作，
if you're watching this and you work in tech,
你大概会填某种一年两次的 Culture Amp
you probably answer some sort of biannual culture amp.
式的调查，问你感觉如何，
Style survey about how you're feeling,
但那些问题的深度，无非就是你所在公司的
but the questions don't really dive any deeper than the effectiveness of your
经理或领导层是否称职。
manager or leadership at the company you work at.
而这项调查的整体情况，
Whereas the big picture in this survey and,
我想最让我们印象深刻的是，如今从业者群体的
and I think the the thing that stood out to us the most is how bifurcated the
分化程度有多严重。
workforce is right now.
你会看到，AI 带来了
And what you're going to see is that AI has.
一种异常巨大的影响，左右着人们对工作的感受，
An outlier level, outsize impact on how people feel about their work more
其影响超过工作的任何其他因素，无论是职位、
so than any other, uh, characteristic of their job, whether it's their role,
所在公司、公司规模、职级等等。
the company they work for, the company size, their level, etcetera.
一半的科技从业者感到无比振奋、能力被放大，
Half of the people in tech are feeling incredible energized, amplified,
对这项技术以及自己职位的未来充满期待。
excited about the technology and the future of, you know, their role.
而另一半人则觉得未来不明朗，感到不安。
And the other half feel like the future is unclear. They feel destabilized.
他们感到被削弱，以及其他类似的负面情绪。
They feel diminished. Other negative emotions around that.
这是一幅非常有意思的图景，
It's, uh, it's a very interesting picture
它把科技从业者一分为二，我们稍后就会看到。
that really cuts the tech workforce in half and that's what we'll see in a second.
感觉确实如此，当我们观察科技从业者时，
It feels so like, yes, this feels correct as we, we look at people in tech,
这种现象真的非常明显。
like it just, uh, is so clear that this happening.
有意思的是，结果正好是五五开。
And what's interesting is it's 50, 50 in the results.
这出乎我的意料，所以这本身就是个很有意思的发现。
I didn't expect to be. So even that was a really interesting takeaway.
是五五开。但当你再深入分析数据时，
It's 50 50. When you dive a little bit deeper into the data,
会发现其中还有一些细微差别。
there is some nuance there.
我们现在看的这张幻灯片上是这个问题，
So we're looking at this slide with the question that you
你和我都决定作答的那个调查问题，
and I both decided to answer the survey,
那就是：AI 是否以及如何改变了你的职业身份？
which is how has AI shifted your professional identity if at all?
首先我要指出的是，
And I'll actually call out first of all,
只有 3% 的人表示 AI 没有改变他们的身份认同。
that only 3% of people reported that AI hasn't shifted their identity.
所以很明显，AI 改变了我们每个人看待自己的方式。这是第一点。
So clearly, AI has changed how we each view ourselves. That's first of all.
而正如你所说，这里最突出的一点是，
But then to your point, the most prominent thing here is
有 50% 的科技从业者感到能力被放大了。
that 50% of people in tech are feeling amplified.
他们觉得自己能做更多的事。
They feel like they can do more.
他们觉得自己能做得更好。这是一种完全正面的
They feel like they can do better. It's a wholly positive, uh,
情绪，非常棒。
emotion and it's great.
很棒，对他们来说很棒。
It's great. It's great for them.
但另一半科技从业者又分成三个明显不同的群体。
But the other half of tech divide into three distinct groups.
第一类人觉得自己的职位正在被重新定义。
The first group is people who feel like their role is being redefined.
这个群体其实并没有
They don't, that group doesn't actually have
对眼前变化有多清晰的认识，也没有明确的正面或负面情绪。
that much clarity or specific positive or negative emotions around what's happening.
他们只是不太理解这一切。
They just don't really understand it.
这是一种非常复杂的情绪：我很清楚
It's a very mixed bag type of emotion where it's very clear to me
自己的职位正在发生根本性变化，但我不太清楚这意味着什么。
that my role is fundamentally changing, but I don't really know what it means.
这类人占我们样本的 27%。
And that's 27% of our sample.
再往下看，还有两个群体对眼前的变化
Then as we go down the line, we have two groups who have clear negative emotions
抱有明确的负面情绪。
around what's going on.
第一个群体，14% 的人感到不安动摇。
The first group, 14% of people feel destabilized.
就好像脚下的地面在震动。
You know, the the ground is shaking beneath them.
他们对眼前发生的事几乎没有清晰认识，焦虑水平很高。
They have very little clarity on what's going on. They have high anxiety levels.
他们表示自己对未来抱有非常负面、
They report having, uh, very negative and, and, uh,
悲观的看法。
pessimistic views of what's to come.
然后有 5% 的人感到被削弱。
And then 5% of people feel diminished.
他们觉得 AI 的强大能力从他们身上夺走了某些东西，
They feel like the great powers of AI have taken something away from them
而且显然再也回不来了，因为那句话怎么说来着？
and something that obviously is never going to come back because what's the saying?
AI 模型的今天，是它们此后最差的状态。
AI and air models are the worst today that they'll ever be.
它们只会越来越好。
They're only getting better.
所以现在感到被削弱的人，未来很可能只会觉得被削弱得更厉害。
So people who feel diminished now will only feel more diminished in the future probably.
好的。顺着这个思路，抱歉带来了坏消息。
Super. So following that thread, sorry for the bad news.
抱歉说了坏消息，不过这里也有一些好消息。
Sorry for the, the bad, there's, there's some good news here.
那么顺着这个思路，
So following that thread, uh, this,
这几个分组与几乎所有其他衡量人们状态的指标
these buckets correlate super strongly with basically every other measure of how
都高度相关。
people are doing.
在你问的几乎每一个核心问题上，都能看到这种回归关系。
See this kind of regression on just like every other core, uh, question you asked.
看到它们之间联系如此紧密，真的很有意思。
And, and it's so interesting to see how connected these are.
是的，再用几个统计学术语来说明一下，
Yeah, and just to put a couple of statistical terms on this to,
来说明这个影响到底有多大。
to clarify how big the effect is.
在科技行业，我们有点痴迷于统计显著性这个概念。
In tech, we are somewhat obsessed with the notion of statistical significance.
但统计显著性的问题在于，
But the thing about statistical significance is that
如果你的样本足够大，
if you have a large enough sample,
无论这个影响在实际中有多重要，
you can sort of reach that type of significance regardless of how much the effect
你都能达到那种显著性。
matters practically.
更好的方法是用效应量指标，比如这里用的 Cohen's d。
A better way to look at things is using an effect size measure like Cohen's d in in this case.
效应量告诉你的是，这件事在实际中到底有多重要。
And what effect size tells you is practically how much does this thing matter?
举个例子，去年我们看到的几个最大影响是：第一，
So for example, last year a couple of the largest effects we saw were, No..
你的经理，你的经理是谁，
1, your manager, who your manager is
以及他们有多称职，对你是否享受工作影响巨大，
and how effective they are matters a ton to how much you're enjoying your job
也影响你有多乐观、有多倦怠。
and how optimistic you are and how burnt out you are or not.
这些我们稍后会看到。
We'll see some of that later on.
我们发现的第二大影响是创始人幸福效应。
And the second large effect we found was the founder happiness effect.
那些目前正在创业的创始人，
Founders at these people who are currently founders
在经营初创公司的过程中非常幸福，可能是
and in their journey of running a startup are incredibly happy probably
因为相较于普通员工，他们拥有更多的掌控权和自主权。
because they have lots of agency and and autonomy relatively to, um,
就是普通员工。
the typical employee.
这个关于 AI 对你身份认同影响的发现，
This finding this insight around the impact of AI on your identity
以及它对你工作相关的每一个其他变量的影响，大约是
and on every single other variable around your job is about three times as large
那些其他影响的三倍。
as those other effects.
所以我们所处的这项技术、这个时代，正在产生一种异常巨大的
So this technology, this era that we're in is having an outlier level outsized
对人们工作感受的影响，超过我们见过的任何其他因素。
impact on how people are feeling about work more so than anything else we've seen.
那我们来看看这份数据，看这种分类是如何
So let's actually look at that data of just how this sort of classification connects
与乐观、倦怠这类因素关联的。
to just optimism, burnout, things like that.
因为这个，我们之后会再回来讨论这个分化到底
Uh, because this is, and we're going to come back to just like what exactly is
是什么，就是一个能告诉你你站在哪一边的问题。
that divide, just the question to ask that tells you which side you're on?
但我们先看这个。
But let's look at this first.
是的，我们稍后会更深入地探讨其中一些内容。
Yeah. So we'll dive into some of these things in a little more depth later on.
但先把它们整合起来看，
But just to put it all together,
你现在看到的是 AI 身份认同立场，
what you're looking at here is the AI identity stance
然后按你的身份认同拆分为职业乐观度、倦怠、裁员担忧等。
and then a breakdown by your a identity around career optimism, burnout, layoff, worry.
对我来说有一个很有意思的点，我们会进一步讨论，
And an interesting one for me, and we'll talk about this further,
你会不会向现在刚入行的人推荐你的岗位，
would you recommend your role to someone coming into the industry now
你能看到，从那些感觉被增强的人，转到
and what you can see is that as you move from the people who feel amplified to the
那些感觉被削弱的人，职业乐观度显著下降。
people who feel diminished, career optimism goes down significantly.
倦怠，或对倦怠的报告显著上升。裁员。
Burnout or reports of burnout go up significantly. Layoff.
担忧也显著上升，
Worry also rises significantly,
而其中最重要的发现或许是，
and perhaps the most significant finding of them all is that.
人们不会建议初级人员、
People would not recommend junior people,
处于职业早期的人在此刻进入科技行业，
early career people entering into the tech workforce at this moment,
考虑到 AI 正在带来的变化。
given what's happening with AI.
你看到的是这些非常线性、清晰、有规律的影响，
And you're seeing these very linear, clear and organized effects,
这恰恰向你展示了
which just demonstrates to you the impact
AI 对所有这些不同变量所产生的影响。
that AI is having on all of these different variables.
我很喜欢的一点是，你把所有这些数据点
And what I love is you took all of this kind of all these data points
归纳出了当今四种人的原型。
and you've created these kind of four archetypes of people today.
我觉得每个听众都会说，好吧，那就是我。
And I feel like everyone listening is going to be like, okay, that's me.
那我们来过一遍。
So let's go through that.
是的，我们看到了这四类科技从业者，
Yeah, so we're seeing these these four tech workers
我们得出这个结论的方式是，在调查后段，
and the way we got to this is later on in the survey,
我们询问人们的感受，让他们报告具体的情绪。
we asked people about how they're feeling and to report specific emotions.
人们可以选择任意多种情绪，对吧。
And people could choose as many emotions as they wanted. Right.
顺便说个有趣的事实，平均来说，人们选了五种不同的情绪。
And by the way, fun fact, on average, people selected five different emotions.
我记得有几个人选了 13 种他们正在感受的情绪，那可真多。
And I think a couple of people selected 13 emotions that they're feeling, which is a lot.
我们发现的第一种原型是充满干劲的科技从业者，
So the first archetype we found is the energized tech worker,
占我们样本的 41%。
and that's 41% of our sample.
这些人会说，做产品又变得有趣了。
These are the people who were saying, that product has become fun again.
我在探索各种东西。
I'm exploring things.
我感觉自己像置身于一个科技游乐园，一切都向我敞开。
I feel like I'm in the tech amusement park where everything is open to me
我可以尝试新的方法。
and I can experiment with new approaches.
我现在是个 builder，拥有了以前从未有过的能力，等等。
I'm a builder now. I have powers that I've never had before, etc.
这些人对技术和自己的职业充满干劲。
These people are very energized about the technology and about their their careers.
第二类人我们称之为矛盾者，那个摇摆的中间群体。
The second group we called the conflicted, the ambivalent middle.
他们占样本的 35%。
These are 35% of the sample.
这些人一方面正经历着，
These are people who are having on the one hand,
作为 builder、PM、设计师、工程师，
the most fun they've ever had as builders, as PMS, as designers, as engineers,
或任何角色，最开心的一段时光。
whatever their role is.
另一方面，他们又感受到前所未有的不确定，
And on the other hand, they're feeling the most uncertainty
那是他们职业生涯中从未有过的。他们完全看不懂。
that they've ever felt in their careers. They just don't understand.
这一切要走向何方，也不知道自己正在打造的东西
Where this is going and whether they're building the things
最终会不会终结他们所熟悉的职业生涯。
that will ultimately lead to the end of their careers as they know it.
第三类原型是迷失者，
The third archetype are the disoriented people,
那些觉得自己的角色不断变动的人。
the people who feel like their role keeps shifting.
我们看到一位受访者的一句话，
There's a quote that we saw from one of the the respondents,
我们就像工业革命前夕的农民，
we're like farmers on the cusp of the industrial revolution,
完全看不清眼前发生的一切通往何处。
and we just don't see a clear path to what's happening.
与那个时代的对比很有意思。
Very interesting comparison to, to that era.
这些人对自己职业中正在发生的事
And these are people who are feeling very disoriented around what's going on in
以及一切的走向感到非常迷茫。
their career and where things are, are leading.
最后，样本中有 12% 被我们归类为怨愤者。
And then finally, 12% of the sample we categorized as resentful.
他们感到有压力，也感到心灰意冷。
They're feeling pressured, they're feeling checked out.
他们现在并不享受自己的工作。
They are not enjoying their work right now.
他们会说，我被迫要么用 AI，要么丢工作。
They're saying things like I've been forced to use AI or lose my job.
而且就算我用了 AI，还是看到有人丢了工作。我实在讨厌这样。
And even when I use AI, I'm still seeing people lose their jobs. I just hate it.
你知道，我很讨厌。
You know, I, I hate.
讨厌不得不去用这项技术，而不能做自己的事，
Having to leverage this technology rather than do my own my own thing
或者干脆无视这项技术——当然，如今我们谁都无法无视它。
and maybe ignore the technology, which obviously none of us can ignore at this point.
显然有很多人非常不开心、怨愤、迷茫。
There's a lot of people clearly that are very unhappy, resentful, disoriented.
我想那群人很难想象有很多人感到无比振奋，
I imagine that group can't imagine a lot of people are feeling extremely energized
反过来也一样。
and I think the vice versa.
所以我觉得看到这一点真的很有意思，
So I think this is just like really interesting to see
很多人和你截然不同。
that many people are very different from you.
有很多人过得很不错，
There are many people that are having a really good time,
也有很多人过得很糟。
a lot of people that are having a really bad time.
这提醒我们要记住这一点，
And it's just a good way to remember and give
对另一半人抱有同理心，
and basically have empathy for the other half,
尤其是那些过得不太好的人，因为不是每个人都那么有干劲。
especially the folks not doing as well because not everyone is as energized.
我们稍后会聊聊那个充满干劲的群体是什么样。
And we'll talk about like what that energized groups look group looks like.
但我觉得这一点很重要。
But I think that's just an important point.
很多人正过得很艰难。
Like a lot of people are having a really hard time.
我非常认同你，Lenny。
I, I really agree with you, Lenny.
我觉得考虑到技术变化的速度，
And I think that given the pace of change of the technology, I,
我真的觉得我们把太多精力花在了掌握技术、
I really do feel that too much of our focus is being spent on mastering the
以及琢磨这些新版本到底该怎么用上。
technology and trying to understand what the heck we should be doing with these new releases.
新模型、新能力，呃，loop engineering，
New models, new capabilities, uh, loop engineering,
还有下周会冒出来的下一个新东西。
whatever the next thing will be next week.
而我们没有花足够的时间和精力去经营工作中的关系，
And we're not spending enough time and focus on our relationships at work,
去关注同事，去支持身边的人，让他们也能
on seeing our colleagues, on supporting our peers in also being able to, you know,
用好这项技术，靠它成长、成功，
work with this technology, thrive with it, succeed with it and.
也能和那些与我们不属于同一类的人好好相处、协作，
And get along and collaborate well with people who don't belong in the same bucket
尤其是在如何看待这项技术这件事上。
as us when it comes to how the technology is being perceived.
所以我个人很希望看到我们所有人，尤其是充满干劲的人，
So I personally would love to see all of us, especially energized people,
拿出一部分这种能量，投入到身边的人身上，
take some of that energy and spend it on the people around you
而不是全心扑在 AI 的下一个新东西上。
rather then the all in focus on whatever the next thing is with with AI.
我们进入下一个要点吧。聊聊职业倦怠和乐观情绪。
Let's go to the next takeaway. Let's talk about burnout and optimism.
好，去年我们研究了职业倦怠，也研究了乐观情绪。
Yeah, so last year, we looked at burnout and we looked at optimism.
当时职业倦怠已经到了令人担忧的程度，于是我们为此发布了进一步的研究，
And burnout was at a worrying level enough that we published further research on it,
并提出了 ARMOR 框架，用来应对
and we introduced the armor framework around how to deal with burnout
和对抗职业倦怠。
and fight burnout.
而这一次，我也说不好自己原本期待的是什么。
And this time around, I'm not sure what I was expecting necessarily.
我想我本来希望乐观情绪能保持稳定，倦怠感不会上升。
I think I was hoping that optimism would hold steady and that burnout wouldn't go up.
因为按理说，有了新能力和更强的模型，
Because supposedly with new abilities and even better models,
也许你会以为我们不必那么拼命，或者，
perhaps you might think that we wouldn't have to work as hard or, or,
或者不必在每件事上都投入到让自己精疲力竭的程度。
or put as much energy into everything in a way that gets us burnt out.
但从严重倦怠的数据来看，情况并非如此，
And yet that's not what we're seeing when it comes to significant burnout,
也就是超过中度的倦怠。
burnout that's higher than moderate.
我们从 2025 年的 44.7% 上升到了 2026 年的 54.7%。
We've gone up from 44.7% in 2025 to 54.7% in 2026.
所以倦怠感正在激增。
So burnout is surging.
目前我们样本中超过一半的人都感到严重倦怠。
More than half of our sample are feeling significantly burnt out at this point.
与此同时，对我们职位未来的乐观情绪
And at the same time, optimism around the future of our roles
以及对职业前景的乐观，从 2025 年的 54.8% 降到了 2026 年的 48.7%。
and our careers is for from 54.8% in 2025 to 48.7% in 2026.
对科技圈来说是坏消息。
Bad news for the tech community.
除了说一句"太糟了"，我不知道还能说什么。
I don't know what to say about this other than that sucks.
我不喜欢这个结果。呃，但我完全理解。就是说，
I don't like this. Uh, I get it fully. Like,
我完全能理解人们为什么会有这种感受。
I can completely understand why people are feeling this.
呃，相当令人担忧，倦怠感一年内就大幅跳升，
Uh, pretty worrisome the, the rise to like a massive jump like over 10% increase in
涨幅超过 10%。
burnout in just in a year.
是啊，有意思的是，你以前请过好几位嘉宾，
Yeah, and it and it's interesting you've had several guests on in the past who,
他们都谈到过与此相关的话题。
who've talked about things related to this.
我很喜欢你和 Ramp 的 Jeff 那期对话。
I loved your conversation with uh, Jeff, uh, from ramp.
呃，他说过他最严重的倦怠发生在效率最低的时候。
Um, and he shared that his worst burnout happened when velocity was lowest.
也就是当你努力去做的事情却毫无进展时，感觉很糟。
So when you put effort into things that don't actually move, it doesn't feel good.
这就导致了倦怠。
And that leads, uh, to burnout.
我觉得这跟一些关于倦怠的理论对得上，
And I think that maps for me with certain theories around burnout,
也就是停滞会导致倦怠。
where stagnation leads to burnout.
我觉得现在的情况恰恰相反。
I think what's going on now is the opposite.
这些数据表明，随着我们交付的速度前所未有地快，
These data showcase to you that as we ship faster than ever,
从一天提交几个 PR 变成一天 30 个 PR，
as we move from shipping, you know, a couple of PRs a day to 30 PRs a day or,
或者干脆做多得多的事情。
or just doing so much more.
某种程度上这可能挺有意思，但我们比以前更容易倦怠。
In some ways that might be fun, but we are burning out more than, than we did before.
而且很明显，我们并没有工作得更轻松，对吧？
And, and we're not working any less hard, clearly. Right?
我们只是承担了更多东西，更多原型，更多 PRD，
We, we, we're just taking on more stuff, more stuff, more prototypes, more PRDs,
更多 PR，更多营销活动，更多 agents，更多广告。
more PRs, more campaigns, more agents, more ads.
这就导致了更多的倦怠。
And it's leading to more burnout.
是的，这其实也是我们后面会讲到的一个要点。
Yeah. And that's actually one of the takeaways which we'll get to.
呃，不知道你这份幻灯片里有没有，
Uh, I don't know if you have this in this deck,
但你指出的一线希望是，
but the a glimmer of hope that you pointed out is
人们对工作的享受度其实依然很高，虽然倦怠严重，
that enjoyment of work is actually still very high, that it's burnout,
但人们对工作的享受度仍和去年持平，是真的很享受工作。
but also people still at the same levels last year actually really enjoying their work.
我觉得关于享受度，我们听到最多的，
I think what we heard about enjoyment more than anything else,
这确实让我看到希望。
which does give me hope.
有这么几点。
Is it's a couple of things.
我想，呃，首先，人们能够展现出自己身份和热情中
I think, um, first of all, people are able to bring out certain aspects of their
以前无法展现的某些方面。
identity and of their passions that they weren't able to before.
比如说，如果你现在的职位是 PM。
You know if, if you're currently a PM by role.
但你内心其实有个设计师，或者你是做营销的，
But you have a, a designer within you or you're a marketer,
但内心深处其实住着一个一直想释放出来的工程师。
but really inside you have that engineer that's been really wanting to, to come out.
现在你可以了，对吧？
Now you can, right?
呃，如今我们能用到的各种工具，让你能够展现出
Um, various tools that are available to us these days enable you to bring out those
你性格中的那些面向，以及那些职业上的追求。
sides of your personality and those professional aspirations.
这正是人们真正享受的东西。
And that's something that people are really enjoying.
我们某种程度上正在跳出传统的职责分工，
We're sort of escaping our classic swim lanes
而且有一定比例的岗位正在转型为别的东西。
and a certain percentage of our roles are transforming into something else.
然后人们说的第二件
And then the second thing that people are saying
让他们觉得享受的事情是，呃，他们能够。
that they're finding enjoyable is that, um, they are able.
把他们一直想打造的东西变成现实，
To manifest things that they've wanted to build
那些不久前还看似不可能的东西，你懂的，呃，
that seemed impossible not very long ago, you know, um, and that,
无论是在主业中，还是在做的副业里，等等。
and that's whether it's in their main job or things that they're doing on the side, et cetera.
所以对很多科技从业者来说，这仍然是，
So it is still for many people in tech,
这是一个激动人心、令人愉快的时代，因为我们能做到一些事
an exciting time and an enjoyable time because we can do things
那些我们从没想过能做到、超出我们职责范围的事
that we never thought we'd be able to do because they're outside of our role.
因为它们超出了原本技术上可行的范围，或者出于其他原因
Because they're outside of what felt technically feasible or for other reasons.
这是另一个数据点，在最后
And this is another data point in the at the end of this,
你会给出一系列建议，告诉大家如何运用这些信息
you have a bunch of recommendations of what to do with all this information and
这和你后面提出的一个建议是相关的
that connects to something that you recommend later.
但在讲到那之前，另一个非常有意思的发现是关于
But before we get there, one of the other really interesting takeaways was around
裁员，以及对裁员的恐惧如何影响职业倦怠
layoffs and how layoffs impact fear of layoffs impact burnout.
聊聊这个吧
Talk about that.
我们确实问过大家有多担心被裁员
We did ask people how worried they are about being laid off.
如你所见，我们样本中有 72% 在一定程度上担心
And as you can see, 72% of our sample are worried to a certain extent about being
被裁员，41.2% 至少中等程度地担心被裁员
laid off and 41.2% are at least moderately worried about being laid off.
所以很明显，人们感觉自己在使用 AI 时
So it is clear that people are feeling that they might be cutting the branch
可能是在砍掉自己坐着的那根树枝
that they're sitting on when it comes to using AI.
人们反映，他们的公司正全力押注 agents
People are reporting that their company is going all in on agents,
全力押注这些技术，确实让人觉得自己迟早可能被挤出去
all in on these technologies and it does feel like they may be pushed out at some point.
所以这种担忧程度是很高的
So that the worry level is, is high.
我想，如果你正在看这个视频
And I think if you're watching this,
你会开始注意到，如今这个圈子里存在着大量的矛盾心态
you're starting to notice that there's a ton of ambivalence right now in the
以及大量情绪之间的冲突
community and a ton of clashes between emotions,
一方面感到充满干劲、享受自己的工作
feeling energized and enjoying my job
与此同时又对它不太乐观，并因此感到疲惫
and at the same time not being very optimistic about it and feeling tired from it.
还担心这一切的乐趣会有一天结束
And feeling worried that all of that enjoyment is going to end one day
当我所在的公司决定不再需要我的时候
when the company I work for decides that I'm no longer needed.
我觉得很多正在听的人可能都
I feel a lot of people listening are probably feeling,
感同身受，觉得被理解了
feeling all this and feeling heard.
有意思的是，到目前为止，大致有两个发现
So what's interesting is so far, the kind of two takeaways.
一个是正在发生的这种分化，以及那些进一步细分这个群体的
One is this bifurcation that's happening and these kind of archetypes that break
典型类型
that group a little bit further.
与此同时，整体来看，职业倦怠正在显著上升
At the same time, just broadly, burnout is increasing significantly,
乐观情绪正在下降
optimism is declining.
就聊聊这两点吧，你是怎么把这两者放在一起看的
Talk about just those two, kind of how you think about those two side by side,
一方面很多人更快乐了，正处于人生最好的时光
this idea of many people are much happier and having the best time of their life.
另一方面有些人过得非常糟糕
People are having a really bad time.
但从大局看又有这种乐观和倦怠的变化
But then broadly this optimism and burnout shift.
我觉得这项技术有某种让人上瘾的地方
I think there's something addictive about this technology.
我就以自己为例说一句
And I'll speak for myself for a second and say that, you know,
我职业生涯里从没像使用这些技术时这么快乐过
I've also never had as much fun in my career as when using these technologies.
我每天用它的时间太长了，一边玩一边做东西
And I've been using it for too many hours a day, playing about and building.
我觉得我们很多人，即便是那些对技术没那么兴奋的人
I think many of us, even those who aren't as energized about the technology,
也仍然觉得自己身处一个迷人的技术游乐场，而且非常
we still feel like we're in this fascinating technological playground, and it's very,
非常难从这项技术里抽身出来，去接触真实生活、读本书
very hard to disengage from that technology and touch grass, read a book.
或者做任何你在闲暇时喜欢做的事，Lenny
Whatever you love to do in in your spare time as well, Lenny.
所以，是的，我们享受使用这项技术，因为它打开了
And so, yes, we're enjoying using this technology because it's opened up avenues
我们从未有过的许多途径
that we've never had.
但另一方面，它也让人疲惫
But on the other hand, it's tiring.
不断学习这项技术让人疲惫
It's tiring to be constantly learning this technology
不断尝试把它应用到不同场景中
and constantly trying to apply it in different contexts
不断尝试承担超出传统职责范围的工作
and constantly try to take on more than what your traditional role dictated.
因为，再说一次，如今已经没有什么传统职责了
Because, again, there aren't any traditional roles anymore.
如今我们都是 builders（构建者）
We're just all builders these days,
无论这在公司里是不是一个正式的头衔
whether that's an official thing within a company or not.
所以我认为这自然而然地引出了这些相互冲突的情绪
And so I think that naturally this leads to these, these clashing emotions,
这些令人兴奋的感受
these exciting feelings.
围绕着能实现什么、用 AI 有多有趣，而另一方面又意识到
Around what's possible and how fun it is to use AI, and on the other hand, the realize.
这项技术之所以如此令人兴奋，是因为它如此强大
That the reason this technology is so exciting is because it's so powerful
而正因为它如此强大，它可能会冲着我们来、抢走我们的工作，对吧
and because it's so powerful, it might be coming for us and to take our jobs, right.
你是看着 Terminator（终结者）系列电影长大的吗
Did you, did you grow up on the Terminator movies?
我一直想到 Terminator 系列电影
I keep thinking about the Terminator movies.
说长大可能算不上，但确实，我很早就看过它们
I don't know about growing up, but yes, I, I watched them early in my.
天啊，我超爱那些电影。
Oh my gosh, I love those movies.
我总忍不住想，机器人什么时候会来对付我们。
And I just can't help but wonder, you know, when the robots are coming for us.
所以，某天这种惊人的技术可能会冲着我们来。Skynet。
So, uh, incredible technology might be coming for us at some point. Skynet.
Skynet 现在正在被打造。
Skynet is being built right now.
就在此刻，Skynet 正在成型。它就要来了。所以有个，
Skynet, as you speak. Skynet is coming. So there's a,
关于这一点会有一个很棒的结论。
there's gonna be a really great takeaway around this.
不过在讲到那个之前，呃，
Before we get to that one actually, uh,
每一条都太有意思了，真的，天啊，
it's like every single one is so interesting and just like, man,
这条很有趣，但它们全都很有趣。
this one's interesting, but they're all interesting.
我们来看下一个结论，关于人们对自己职业的感受，
Let's get to the next takeaway around people's sense of their own career
以及他们是否愿意推荐它。
and whether they recommend it.
这一条对我来说很震撼，因为至少在研究圈里，
This is a wild one for me because at least within the research community,
我以厌恶净推荐值（NPS）出名。
I am known as the net promoter score hater.
我甚至建了个专门反对 NPS 的网站，叫 NPSistheworst.com。
I even built a website dedicated to fighting NPS. NPS is the worst dot com.
这是个真实存在的网站。顺便说个趣事，我，
It's an actual website. Fun fact, by the way, I,
我太讨厌 NPS 了，甚至还买下了域名。
I dislike NPS so much that I even bought the domain.
NPSisthebest.com，然后把访客都转到 NPSistheworst.com。
NPS is the best dot com and I forward people from that to NPS is worst.com.
我就是这么执着于反对 NPS。
That's how committed I am to fighting NPS.
但是。
But.
但你和我都真心好奇，那些已经，
But you and I were both genuinely curious about whether people who are, you know,
入行几年、可能已是资深或更高级别的人，
already a few years in and they may be senior or above senior in their roles,
会对现在刚入行的人说什么，或者会对，
what would they say to the person entering the industry now or what would they say
正在考虑入行的人说什么？
to a person considering entering the industry now?
他们会向朋友或亲戚推荐自己的岗位，以及科技，
Would they recommend their role and. And the tech.
乃至整个科技行业吗？
Industry more broadly to a friend or relative of theirs.
答案令人震惊，绝对震惊。
And the answer was shocking, absolutely shocking.
那我来给你看看相关数据，
So let me show you the data around this
先简单解释一下 NPS，
and let me preface this with a quick explanation on NPS,
因为它并不容易理解。
because it's not so easy to understand.
NPS 就是问你是否愿意推荐一款产品，或者在这里，
NPS is this question around whether you would recommend a product or in this case,
你的岗位给朋友或家人，对吧？
your role to a friend or family member, right?
打分从 0 到 10，
And the scale goes from 0 to 10,
10 代表你绝对会推荐你的岗位，
10 being you would absolutely recommend your role
0 代表你绝对不会推荐你的岗位。
and zero being you would absolutely not recommend your bowl.
而 NPS 整体计算出来的范围是从负 100，
But then NPS as a whole, when it's calculated, goes from minus 100,
也就是糟透了，到正 100。
which is absolutely terrible to plus 100.
0 分代表中立。
And the 0 point represents neutrality.
代表整个样本处于中立状态。
It represents that the sample as a whole is neutral.
用 NPS 的说法，它不是推荐者。呃，
It's not a promoter to use nps. Uh,
意思是我会向别人推荐我的岗位。
speak meaning I would promote my role to other people.
我会推荐给别人，同时他们也不是贬损者，
I would recommend it to other people and they're not detractors either,
也就是我对自己的岗位没有负面评价。
which means I'm not negative about my role.
这就是零点。
So that's the zero point.
你在这里看到的是，现在没有人会推荐自己在科技行业的岗位。
What you're seeing here is that no one is a promoter of their role in tech right now.
就连创始人也不会，而他们目前是科技圈里最开心、最乐天的一群人。
Not even founders who are by far the happiest happy go lucky people in in tech right now.
创始人也不会推荐自己的岗位。
Founders would not recommend their roles.
销售、市场推广、PM、运营、工程等岗位的人也不会，
Neither would people in sales or go to market, PMS, operations, engineering,
而最糟的是设计师和研究员。
and the worst of all, designers and researchers.
我所在的群体最不可能向想进入科技行业的人推荐自己的岗位。
My community are the least likely to recommend their role to other people coming into tech.
这就像是在说，我正泡在这个泳池里，
It's sort of like saying, you know, I'm, I'm kind of swimming in this pool.
水还算可以，但你不该跳进这片科技的水域。
The water's kind of okay, but you shouldn't come into these, these tech waters.
这里不适合你。
They ain't for you.
天啊，这个结论太有意思了。
My God, what a interesting takeaway.
而作为这项研究的一部分，
And, and part of this research,
我正和大家一起看着这张图表，呃，
so I'm just looking at this chart just as people are seeing this, uh,
就像没人愿意，每个人都在说，别，别做我这行。
just like nobody, everyone's like, no, don't do what I do.
这很有意思，你知道，
It's interesting like, you know,
我们会聊到创始人是科技圈里最幸福的人，但即便如此，
we're going to talk about how founders are the happiest people in tech, but still,
这仍是一份压力极大、非常艰难的工作。
it's like a very stressful, hard job.
呃，我很意外。真的，我很意外。
Uh, I'm surprised. It's like, I'm surprised.
这种情况最不像很多人以为的创始人该有的样子。
It's the least like you would think many founders would be like this.
最疯狂、最棘手的工作，你不该去做。它很糟，但很有意思。
So the craziest, gnarliest job you should not do. This sucks, but it's interesting.
他们最不算不快乐，但也最不愿意推荐这份工作。
They're the least unhappy, but they're the least, least likely to recommend.
现在有一种很强的说法，
There's a strong narrative right now
说现在是当创始人的最佳时机。
that there's never been a better time to be a founder.
你在做产品时对别人的依赖大大减少了。
You're a lot less reliant on other people to build.
关于一人创业者的讨论铺天盖地。
There's a ton of conversations around the solopreneur.
或者双人创业者，对吧。
Or the duopreneur, right.
很多讨论都在说，现在正是当创始人的时代，
There's a ton of conversations around how this is the era to be a founder
然而，那些当下正处在
and yet people who are currently in
这个角色的人，却不太愿意把它推荐给别人。
that role aren't very excited about recommending it to other people.
这里还有另一层：你的职级越低，
There's also another layer to this, which is as you go down in seniority,
你就越不愿意推荐自己的岗位。
you're less likely to recommend your role.
所以高管、VP、甚至总监相对更愿意推荐自己的岗位，
So execs, vps, maybe even directors are sort of more likely to recommend their role
而不是那些 IC（一线执行者）。
than people who are ICS.
这点挺有意思。我见过各种各样的解释。嗯，
That's an interesting one. I've seen all sorts of explanations for that. Um,
比如有一种解释是，
some one explanation, for example, is that.
处在金字塔顶端的 VP 从 AI 中获益更多，
At the top of the pyramid, VPS are benefiting more from AI
因为他们能拿到源源不断的信息，
because they're getting all of this stream of information
以及被 AI 处理过的知识，让他们的工作轻松了很多，
and knowledge being processed by AI, making their jobs a lot easier,
而每个 IC 都在忙着在自己所在的公司里
whereas ICS are each scrambling to build all of these micro SAS products within the
搭建各种微型 SaaS 产品。
companies they work for.
没人知道别人在做什么。
No one knows what anyone else is doing.
有大量重复劳动。
There's a lot of duplicative work.
如今做产品容易多了，但维护起来却难多了。
It's a lot easier to build products these days, but a lot harder to maintain them.
所以我觉得很多 IC 的感受就像那句话：空挡踩到底，对吧？
And so I think a lot of ICS are feeling like there's a saying, full gas on neutral, right?
就像你把油门踩到底，但车却挂在空挡。
Like you're pushing the pedal to the metal in your car, but you're in neutral gear.
你哪儿也去不了。
You're not going anywhere.
我觉得这就是如今很多 IC 面对这些技术时的感受。
I think that that's the feeling that lots of ICS are having these days with these technologies.
就像，我不停地做东西，但没产生我想要的影响力。
Like, I keep building these things, but I'm not having the impact I want.
其他人也都在做。
Everyone else is building, too.
一片混乱，感觉再也不值得了。
There's lots of confusion and it's just not worth it anymore.
还有个挺有意思的趋势，你懂的，就是那整套……
There's like this interesting also trend this, you know, there's this whole.
“别沦为永久底层阶级”的梗。
Mem of don't become part of the permanent underclass.
我觉得这里贯穿着好几条这样的线索。
And I feel like there's like a few of these threads throughout this.
就好像，好吧，我是个 PM，但已经太晚了。
And here it's like, okay, I'm like a PM, but like, it's too late.
别干这行了。这个角色的大门正在关闭。情况在变。
Don't do this. Like the door is closing for this role. Things are changing.
而且这不只是 PM，是每一个岗位。每个人都觉得，
And that's, it's not just PM, it's every role. Everyone's just like,
也许该去干点别的。
maybe should do something else.
是的，我同意。而且我觉得这挺遗憾的。
Yeah, I would agree with that. And I think it's, it's unfortunate.
我觉得过去大家都被推着去学计算机、去学编程。
I, I feel like in the past people were pushed to CS to learn to code.
我知道如今作为一个家长，
I know that these days for myself as a parent, you know,
我已经不知道该让孩子去做什么了。
I don't know what to tell my kids to do anymore.
我不确定短短几年后还会有什么岗位留给他们。
I'm not sure what roles will be there for them in just a few years.
这是个非常令人迷茫的时代，我觉得科技从业者也有同感。
These are very confusing times and I think tech employees are feeling that as well.
他们看不清自己的未来会是什么样。
They don't understand what's in line for them in the future.
所以他们当然也没法向别人推荐说，是啊，你知道的，
So they certainly don't know to recommend to others like, yeah, you know,
五年后一定会很棒。
in five years it's gonna be great.
是啊，就像那句“去搞塑料吧”，没人知道该怎么办。
Yeah, getting the plastics like, yeah, it's like no one knows.
就好像，稍微拉远一点看。
It's just like, just like zoom out for a moment.
我们正经历的变化多得简直疯狂。
It's just, it's so insane how much change we're living through right now.
这不是一两年前会出现的结果。
We would not have, like, this is not a result we would have seen a year or two ago.
这种状态太不稳定、太不确定，对科技行业的人来说都很新鲜。
This is like so unstable and uncertain and this is very new for, for people in tech, I think.
是的，我喜欢用一些比喻，或者说某种，呃，
Yeah, I like to use, uh, certain, uh, metaphors or, or, or sort of, uh,
用我生活中其他领域的例子来解释这些事。
examples from, you know, other, other, uh, areas in my life to explain these things.
我记得你之前采访过 Scott Wu，Cognition 的联合创始人兼 CEO。
So I believe you spoke in the past to uh, Scott Wu, the co founder and CEO Cognition.
嗯，Devin。
Uh huh, Devin.
对，他们就是 Devin 的开发者。
And uh, and they are the makers of Devin.
我记得他在描述这款产品时，谈到了
And I recall that when he described the product, he talked about this,
产品所沿着攀升的这个阶梯。
this ladder that the product progressed on.
它从一个高中 CS 学生，变成大学实习生，再到初级工程师
It went from a high school CS student to a college intern to a junior engineer
到现在可能已经是资深工程师，或者 staff 级别的工程师了
and at this point probably a senior or, or staff level engineer.
可以说，我们都在看着这项技术一级一级爬上这个梯子
I would say that we are all watching this technology climb the rungs of this ladder
不断进阶，而我们感觉这项技术正在抽走我们脚下的横档
and advance, and we feel like the technology is pulling those rungs from under us.
所以我们在梯子上爬得越高
And so the further we've gone up the ladder,
就越对自己的职业感到安心，也越有稳定感
the better we feel about our careers and the more stability we have.
但我们在梯子上的位置越低，脚下的横档就越被抽走
But the lower we are on that ladder, those rungs getting pulled under our feet.
所以我们不愿意推荐别人
And so it makes lots of sense that we wouldn't recommend, you know,
站上这个梯子，也就很合理了，因为横档正在消失
being on that ladder to anyone else because the rungs are disappearing.
天呐，这些内容有太多可聊的了
Man, there's so much to talk about with all these.
但让我在看这些数据时先指出几点
But let me point out a couple things as I look at this
然后我们再进入下一个结论
and then we can move on to the next takeaway.
其中一点是，有意思的是，sales 和 PM 是最不担心的
One is just like, you know, it's interesting that sales and PM are the least, uh, bad at.
不建议进入这个岗位，这很有意思，我没想到
Don't get into this role. Like, that's interesting. I did not.
我没料到会是这样
I wouldn't have expected that.
销售人员没那么害怕，害怕这个岗位的未来。PM 也很有意思
Salespeople not as scared. Scared about the future of the role. PM, interesting,
这在我们的观众里是很大一部分
that's a big audience here.
没那么害怕，正如你所说，research 和 design 是最多人说别做的
Not as scared, as you said, research design the most don't do this.
作为一名 researcher，你稍微提到了这点，但我很好奇
As a researcher, you touch on this a little bit, but I'm just curious,
看到这个结果是什么感受？
how does it feel seeing this, seeing this result?
这挺难受的
It's it's tough.
我觉得 research 群体这些年一直背负着很多担忧和创伤
I think the research community has lived with a lot of concerns and trauma
以及焦虑，围绕着能否在决策桌上有一席之地
and anxiety over the years around having a seat at the table,
围绕着在工作中找到意义
around finding meaning in our work,
围绕着 research 的普及化这类话题
around topics like the democratization of research and, you know.
别人接手我们的岗位，最终取代我们
Other people taking on our roles and eventually replacing us it.
看到这个结果确实很难受。我认为这是一个非常重要的角色
It definitely hurts a lot to see this. I think that's a very important role.
research 在未来的产品打造中需要发挥的作用
That research needs to play in the future of building products.
我认为随着这项技术不断进步
I think that as this technology progressive,
我们对所打造的东西应该更加深思熟虑
we should become even more thoughtful about what we built rather than,
而不是更少去思考
than less thoughtful.
我听过一种说法，就是现在做东西太便宜了
I've heard the narratives around, you know, it's so cheap to build,
直接做一千个原型，看哪个管用
just build 1,000 prototypes and see what works.
我想你在最近的一次对话里也听到过这个
I think you heard this in a recent conversation, uh, as well.
我认为那样做只会让我们更加倦怠
I would suggest that we're just going to get even more burnt out that way.
我个人不推荐那种做法
I would not recommend that approach personally.
我认为 research 和 design 在提升方面都有非常重要的作用
I think research has a very and design has a very important part to play in raising
提升可能性的天花板
the ceiling of what's possible.
而 AI 主要是降低了门槛，但并没有抬高天花板
Um, whereas AI has mostly lowered the bar, but it hasn't hasn't raised the ceiling.
我还可以告诉你，PM 相对更愿意推荐自己的岗位
I can also tell you that PMS being somewhat more likely to recommend their roles
尽管他们总体上并不太愿意推荐，但这对我来说其实说得通
even though they're they're not likely to recommend their roles does actually make sense to me.
我认为，相比其他一些岗位，它更像是一个通才型的角色
It's more of a generalist role, I would claim than some of these other roles.
而这是一个属于通才的时代。如果你问我
And this is the era of the generalist. If you would ask me the.
在 AI 时代，最让我意外的是 sales 和 go to market
The AI era, I'm the most surprised by sales and go to market because
因为如果我们真的处在某种 SaaS 末日之中
if we are indeed in some sort of SAS apocalypse,
我个人并不认为我们是，但你懂的
which I don't personally believe we are, but you know,
有人这么说过，那我觉得 sales
it's been said then I don't think sales
和 go to market 的人不该感觉这么好
and go to market people should be feeling too great.
关于推荐自己的岗位这件事。但也许他们相信
About recommending their roles. Um, but, but maybe they believe that, you know,
现阶段 sales 是 AI 做不了的
sales at this point cannot be done by AI.
是啊，这里有太多我想聊的了
Yeah, there's just like so much I want to talk about here. Uh,
有一点很重要，要指出来
it's important to note.
我接下来要说的这一点非常重要
This is a very important note that I'm going to say here.
这并不意味着 design 会消失，或者 research 会消失
This doesn't mean design is going away or research is going away.
这只是说，现在从事那个岗位的人
This is just saying people in that role right now,
他们脑海里的说法是“别做这行”，但这并不意味着这行完了
the narrative in their head is don't do this does not mean this is over
因为这可能只是我们不断听到的那些炒作
because it could just be all this hype that we keep hearing doesn't like, you know,
各种嘉宾也难辞其咎，包括推波助澜
guilty of adding to it from various guests.
但你知道，这只是人们此刻的感受
But you know, this may. This is just how people feel.
并不代表实际正在发生的就是这样
Doesn't mean that's what's happening.
100%。整个科技领域的这个独特项目，核心就是人们的感受。
100%. This entire unique project in tech is all about how people feel.
它关注的不是科技行业工作的现实，而是人们的情绪，
It's not about the realities of working in tech. It's about people's emotions,
关乎人们的感受。
about how people feel.
嗯，我真的认为除了我们，没人真正捕捉到这些情绪，
Um, I really do think no one other than us has really captured these emotions in the
像我们这样。不过是的，这是个很好的提醒。这并不是……
way that we have. But yeah, it's a great reminder. This is not.
现实的写照。它反映的是科技从业者当下的真实感受。
An image of reality. This is an image of how people are feeling in tech right now.
我们想确保在这里传达的另一个数据点。
Another quick data point that we want to make sure to communicate here.
你提到过这一点，但我不确定你是否真的说得
You touched on this, but I don't know if you actually made this as,
足够清楚，就是，呃，这看的是你会不会……
as clear to people as it should be, is, uh, so this is looking at would you get it,
你会建议别人进入我这个岗位吗？
would you recommend people get into my role?
我们还问了你对自己岗位的感受如何？
We also asked just how are you feeling about your role?
比如，你在这个岗位上开心吗？结果是，
Like, are you happy being in this role? And the result there was,
我其实过得还不错。
I'm actually doing okay.
我很开心。我是PM，我很开心，一名设计师研究员。
I'm happy. I'm a PM. I'm happy a designer researcher.
就像你说的，水温挺好，但别下来。
So as you said, it's this kind of like, the water's fine, but don't get in.
稍微谈谈这一点，确保这个观点清楚。
Talk a little bit about that just to make sure that point is clear.
当我们问人们，呃，他们是否享受自己的工作，
When we asked people things like, uh, are they enjoying their, their job,
正如之前所说，呃，大多数人说总体来说是的。
as we talked about earlier, uh, most people said that overall, yes.
你知道，他们在自己的岗位上，呃，乐在其中。
You know, they're, they're having fun, uh, in, in their role.
我认为这里发生的情况是，再一次，
I think what's going on here is that, again,
人们比过去更缺乏乐观，对吧？
people are lacking optimism compared to what they were, right?
乐观情绪下降了。
Optimism has gone down.
所以人们现在对自己岗位的感受之间有很大差异，
So there's a big difference between how people are feeling now about their role,
考虑到他们在职业生涯中取得的成就，
given what they've achieved in their careers and
以及他们所处的职级，相比他们推测未来可能发生的情况——
where they are on the ladder compared to what they're extrapolating might happen in
一年后、三年后。
a year, in three years.
五年后。
In five years.
而人们推测可能发生的情况，明显比他们
And what people are extrapolating might happen is clearly more negative than their
当前的经历更悲观。
current experiences.
所以是的，总的来说，作为一个行业我们还不错，我们乐在其中，
So yeah, I mean, all in all, we're doing okay as an industry where enjoying,
我们在尝试新事物，我们正在经历一场，一场，
we're trying new things, we're experiencing a, a,
我们工作方式的彻底范式转变。
a complete paradigm shift in how we work.
这有一阵子挺有趣，但是，
And that's fun for a while, but it's,
似乎人们觉得事情并没有朝最好的方向发展。
it seems like people feel like this is not going in the best of directions.
当然，我希望大家都能回归，希望大家都好。
And of course, I hope we're all back. I hope we're all well.
我也是。作为一个天生的乐观主义者，我觉得，会没事的。
Me too. As a natural optimist, I'm like, it's gonna be alright.
所以我们拭目以待。
So we'll see.
我也是天生的乐观主义者。
I'm a natural optimist too.
我意识到，到目前为止我们还没有太多进入乐观模式。
And I'm realizing like, so far we haven't been in too much of optimism mode.
所以我希望我们也能达到一些那样的状态。
So I hope we manage to get to some of that as well.
本期节目由Mercury赞助，一种截然不同的银行服务，
This episode is brought to you by Mercury, radically different banking,
深受超过30万创业者喜爱，现在还有command功能。
loved by over 300,000 entrepreneurs and now with command.
我做Mercury的客户已经超过六年了。
I've been a customer of Mercury's for over six years.
我从未想过离开。
I have never once thought about leaving.
Mercury基本上就是由产品人而非银行家打造银行服务的结果。
Mercury is basically what happens when banking is built by product people, not by bankers.
他们让发送发票、转移资金变得如此简单，甚至可以说有趣，
They make it so easy, dare I say fun, to send invoices, move money around,
为我团队的成员设置虚拟卡。
set up virtual cards for folks on my team.
你的银行有API、终端、原生CLI或支持AI的MCP服务器吗？
Does your bank have an API, a terminal, native CLI or an AI ready MCP server?
我想没有。
I don't think so.
就在最近，他们推出了command，
And just recently they launched command,
一个直接内置于Mercury的对话式界面，
a conversational interface built directly into Mercury,
它充当你的财务操作员。
which acts as your financial operator.
我一直用command来转移资金，弄清楚我在哪些类别上
I've been using command to transfer money around to figure out what categories I've
花钱最多，分析我的现金流。
been spending the most money in, analyze my cash flows.
就在今天，我用它查出过去一年里我从某个特定赞助商那里
And just today, I used it to find out how much I've made from a specific sponsor
赚了多少钱。
over the past year.
我只需问，过去一年我从X赚了多少钱？
I just ask, how much have I made from X over the past year?
10秒后，我就有了答案。这太酷了。
10 seconds later, I have an answer. It is so freaking cool.
访问mercury.com了解更多，几分钟即可在线申请。
Visit mercury.com to learn more and apply online in minutes.
Mercury是一家金融科技公司，而非FDIC承保的银行。
Mercury is a fintech company, not an FDIC insured bank.
银行服务由 Choice Financial Group 和 Column N.A. 提供，二者均为 FDIC 成员。
Banking services provided through Choice Financial Group and Column N.A., members FDIC.
我们来谈谈第四点发现。我们看了生产力，看了质量，
Let's talk about takeaway 4. Looked at productivity, looked at quality,
也就是看 AI 带来的好处。
look at just the kind of the upside of AI.
在我们去年做的调查里，这一点让我很感兴趣，
This was a very interesting one to me in last year's survey
那次调查关注的是 AI 的影响，尤其是对生产力和质量的影响，
that we did on the impact of AI, specifically on productivity and quality,
大家对这项技术相当看好，也很看好它让自己变得更好，
people were rather bullish about the technology and how much better it makes them,
不只是更高效，而是更优秀。
not just more efficient, but better.
而这一次，我们看到了一些有趣的发现。我先从这个说起。
And this time around, we saw some, some interesting findings. Let me start with, with this.
这算是最初的印象，
And this is sort of the initial view,
但它引出的结果和我原本预想的很不一样，
but it leads to something very different than I thought would happen
当我们只是简单问一句：多亏了 AI，你的工作能力提升了多少？
when we simply asked the question, how much better are you at your job thanks to AI?
答案毫无疑问是肯定的。
Unequivocally the answer was yes.
你可以看到，这里有 97.2% 的人表示，
You can see here that 97.2% of people are saying
AI 让他们的工作能力变强了，而且接近 50% 的人表示，
that AI is making them better at their job and close to 50% of people are saying
AI 让他们的工作能力大幅或极大提升。
that AI is making them very much or extremely better at their job.
所以从宏观上很清楚，无论你怎么理解"更好"，
So it's very clear that high level, however you interpret better,
这点我们稍后会讲到，大家都觉得 AI 产生了影响，
which we'll get to in a second, people feel like AI has had an impact,
但当你深入探究它的含义，看到表面之下的东西时，
but when you dive deeper into what that means and you go below the surface level
就像你在这里看到的。
as you can see here.
"我们做得更好"其实指的东西，
We're doing better actually means something
和你想象的很不一样。
rather different than what you might think.
所以当我听到大家说自己做得更好时，我以为是字面意思。
So when I heard people say they're doing better, I thought they meant that literally.
我以为是他们的工作质量更好了，
I thought the quality of their work was better,
以为 AI 让工作质量变得更高。
that AI was contributing to better quality of work.
事实上，恰恰相反。
In fact, it's the exact opposite.
我们从人们那里听到了两件令人担忧的事。
What we heard from people were two concerning things.
第一是"我能更快地做更多，但做得并不更好"。
The first is that I can do more faster, but not better.
所以说，AI 拉低了可能性的下限，
So again, AI has sort of lowered the floor of what's possible and,
让人们的产出量远超以往。
and enabled people to put out a lot more work than they ever have before.
无论那是什么工作，是 PR、PRD、研究项目还是原型，
Whatever that work is, whether it's PRS, PRDS, research projects, prototypes,
但产出的质量并没有更高，
but they're not, the output isn't of higher quality
而或许更令人担忧的影响是我们听到的，
and perhaps the even more concerning effect which we heard about,
这一切更深层的代价，是使用 AI 对思考和判断力造成的损耗。
but the deeper cost of all of this is the cost of using AI on thinking and judgment.
人们基本上是在告诉我们，我的大脑正在
People essentially told us my brain is.
腐烂。
Rotting.
我的工作感觉更差了。
My work feels worse.
这和我最近听说的一个现象有关，就是，呃，
And this, this is related to phenomenon I heard about recently like, um,
我想应该叫"认知腐化"（cognitive rot），我听到的是这个说法。
is it cognitive rot, I think is what, what I've heard.
基本上就是这样一种现象：你看到 AI 模型的初步输出，
Basically this phenomenon where you sort of see the initial output of an AI model
然后就直接接受了。
and you sort of just accept it.
你不对它加以判断，也不加以思考。
You don't apply your judgment to it. You don't apply your thinking to it.
你慢慢地让自己的头脑、对工作的投入，
And you slowly let your, your mind, your involvement in your work,
让自己的主动性，可以说，坍塌进这种腐化状态。
your agency sort of collapse into this rotting state, so speak.
这个。是啊，这真是个很有意思的发现。就是，呃，这算是个积极面。
This. Yeah, this is such an interesting takeaway. Just, uh, like this is a positive.
这里面有个积极的点。
There's a positive note to this.
就像你说的，我在看这里的数据，
As you said, I'm looking at the numbers here,
82% 的人说 AI 至少让他们的工作能力有中等程度的提升，
82% of people say AI is making them at least moderately better at their job,
将近 50% 的人说提升很大或极大，
and nearly 50% say very much or extremely better,
这可能与最初的那种分化相关。
which may correlate with that original just this bifurcation.
也就是说，那些觉得 AI 让自己工作能力变强的人，
Like the people that feel like AI is making them better at their job,
大概就是那些感觉最有干劲的人。
probably the people feel like most energized.
所以不管是不是真的。
So whether it's true or not.
所以我觉得有几个令人欣慰的点。这是其中之一。
So I think there's a couple happy points. That's one.
人们觉得 AI 让自己变得更好了。
People feel AI is making them better.
他们，他们能感受到这一点。所以这，你懂的，即便未必属实，那份感受也是真实的。
They like, they feel that. So that's, you know, that's real even if it may not be.
与此同时，我觉得他们也意识到质量是个问题，
And at the same time, I think they're self aware the quality is an issue
也意识到自己也许正在丧失像写代码或写策略文档这样的能力。
and also I'm just maybe my I'm atrophying in my ability to say code or write strategy docs.
所以至少人们意识到了这种情况正在发生，
So at least people are self aware that this is happening,
而不是觉得"我表现超棒，我做的一切质量都更高，
not just I'm killing it all my stuff is higher quality
比以往好太多了"。
and it's much better than ever.
他们有自我认知。
They are self aware.
但你知道，除此之外，
But you know, among other things,
我是一名认证教练，我想说，除了有自我认知之外，
I'm a certified coach and I would suggest that beyond being self aware,
我们还需要为此采取行动。
we need to act on this.
对于这个现象，我可以给出几种解释。
There are several explanations I could give to this phenomenon.
其中之一可能是，与 AI 的蜜月期结束了。
One of them might be that the honeymoon period with AI is over.
你知道，我们曾以为它完美无缺，
You know, we thought it was perfect and you know, the,
是我们遇到过的最好的事情，
the best thing that ever happened to us
就像典型美国人常说的那种最棒的发明。
since sliced bread or whatever typical Americans say.
嗯，但我们意识到它还没到那个地步。
Um, but we've realized it's not quite there yet.
是的，现在的模型是它们未来最差的时候了。
And yes, the models are the worst they're ever gonna be.
它们只会越来越好，但还有很多地方需要改进，
They're only getting better, but there's still so much they need to get better
我们才能真正说，是的，
before we can really say, yeah, like,
我的工作好太多了，我也不需要那么深入参与。
my work is just so much better and I don't need to be as involved.
参与其中。
With it.
你之前请 Simon Willison 上过这个节目，谈到人们担心
You had Simon Willison on, on this show talking about how people are worried about
技能退化，担心自己学得不够，
skill atrophy, that they're not learning enough,
我们需要有意识地去抵抗这一点，
and that we need to be consciously resistant to this
不要让自己认知退化。
and not let ourselves cognitively rot.
我认为这些数据表明，我们在这场斗争中有点落下风了。
And I think this data suggests that we're losing that fight a little bit.
我们需要为此投入更多精力，
We need to put a little bit more energy into it,
去对抗我们正感受到的这种认知退化，并确保
into fighting this cognitive rot that that we're feeling and to make sure that
随着标准不断提高、技术不断演进，
as the bar continues to rise and this technology continues to evolve.
我们能以刻意练习、刻意思考去应对。
That we're meeting that with deliberate practice, deliberate thinking.
刻意判断。
Deliberate judgments.
人们真的很不擅长这一点。就像如果有个省事的按钮，我就会去按。
People are just so bad at that. Just like if I have an easy button, I will press it.
我知道我不该，但我还是会去吃那些 Doritos。
I know I shouldn't, but I'm just gonna, I'm gonna eat those Doritos.
所以我认为这就是人们面临的挑战。
So that's the challenge I think for people.
就是因为你可以用省事的方式去做，所以很难抵抗。
It's just like because you could do it the easy way, it's so hard to resist.
这又和之前说的那道被抬高的门槛联系起来，
And that connects again to this ladder that's being raised
那些刚入门的人。
that people are just getting into the stuff.
他们必须逼自己用难的方式去做，才能真正学会怎么做。
It's just they have to make themselves do it the hard way to learn how to do it for real.
我很好奇这对市场上那些初级人员会怎样发展，他们要学习
And I'm really curious how that plays out with junior folks in the market learning
如何真正写代码、如何写作，
how to actually code, how to do your writing,
如何亲手从零写一份 PRD，而不是去和 Claude 聊这件事。
how to write a PRD from scratch with your fingers versus talking to Claude about it.
是的，这里有太多可以说的了。
Yeah, there's so much to say here.
我觉得，嗯，人们有时会怀念那种觉得自己聪明的感觉，
I think, um, the, the more I think people miss feeling smart sometimes, you know,
我想我曾经，
I think I, I thought.
曾经觉得自己很聪明，然后你遇到了这些
Once upon a time about myself that I'm, I'm smart and then you encounter these,
这些模型，最近是刚第二次发布的 Fable 5。
these models, most recently fable 5 that just came out for the second time.
你就不再觉得自己那么聪明了，
And you don't feel that smart anymore
你会有点失去过去那种自我效能感。
and you sort of lose the sense of self efficacy that that you used to have.
关于这一点要说的第二件事是，每次是你，而不是 AI，
And, and the second thing to say about this is that every time you, you, not the AI,
解决了一个问题、越过了一道障碍，它就会提升，
solve a problem and get over a barrier, it increases,
它会抬高你自我效能、自信、自我信念的基线。
it raises your baseline of self efficacy, of self confidence, of self belief.
而每次你把这个交给你最喜欢的 AI 模型，
And every time you offload that to your favorite AI model,
你都在降低那个基线，你的思考和判断都在退化，
you're lowering that baseline and your thinking and your judgment is watching,
这是个严重的问题。
and that's a serious problem.
那我们来收尾这个结论吧。我很喜欢这份报告里用的一句话。
So maybe just wrap up this takeaway. The sentence used in this report I love.
我念一下：生产力的提升是真实的，
I'll just read, the productivity gains are real,
但工作的质量、以及产出者本人的敏锐度都受到了冲击。
but the quality of the work and the sharpness of the person producing it are taking a hit.
完全正确。
Absolutely.
嗯，也许我们最后会谈到这一点，
And, well, maybe we'll get to this in the end,
但我们应该密切关注这一点，
but we should keep a close eye on this
并真正努力去提升我们自己的自我效能感。
and really try to work on our own self efficacy.
我们需要针对人的 evals，因为人也需要 evals。
We need like evals for people like are humans because evals for people.
我们来做这个吧，测测你的聪明程度。好的。
Let's, let's do that. Your smartness. Okay.
我们来聊聊第 5 个结论，我觉得它也非常有意思。
Let's talk about takeaway No. 5, which I also thought was extremely interesting.
天哪，这里面太多有意思的内容了。我们来聊聊第五个结论。
My god, so much, so much interesting in this. Let's talk about the fifth takeaway.
是的。我认为现在我们圈子里的主流说法是，
Yeah. So I think the dominant narrative right now in, in our community is,
是被取代的恐惧。
is the fear of being replaced.
正如我们所说，很多科技从业者确实担心、忧虑
And as we talked about, a lot of people in tech do fear and are worried
自己会被取代、会被裁员。
that they're going to be replaced, that they're going to be laid off.
所以按理说，如果我们设置一个问题，
And so it would make sense that if we had a question
而其中一个选项是，
and one of the options to respond to that question were,
“我担心工作被 AI 取代”，它应该排名相当靠前。
I'm worried about losing my job to AI, that it would rank fairly high.
但当我们看这张幻灯片，看到当被问到，
But when we look at this slide and when we look at when people are asked, you know,
你现在的顾虑是什么、什么在困扰你？
what are your concerns and what's bothering you right now?
在科技行业里你在害怕什么？
What, what are you afraid of in tech?
“工作被 AI 取代”其实排在倒数第二。
Losing my job to AI is actually second to last on that list.
相反，升到榜首的是拿同样的薪水却要做更多的事。
And instead what we saw rise up to the top is the expectation to do more for the same pay.
就好像我们都感觉自己被一再压榨、
It's almost as if we're all feeling like we're being squeezed and squeeze
一再压榨，要用更少的时间、同样的薪水完成更多的事。
and squeeze some more to accomplish more things in less time for the same pay.
所以对过度工作的恐惧是目前为止
And so that fear of being overworked is by far the,
最主要的恐惧，与榜单上第二项并列，
the dominant fear alongside the second item in this list,
那就是节奏正变得难以为继。
which is that the pace is becoming unsustainable.
我说的节奏，既指工作的节奏，也指对工作速度的期望，
And by pace, I mean both the pace of the work and the expectation of work velocity,
也就是你每天必须产出多少，
just how much you have to put out a day every single day
以及技术变化的速度。
and the pace of change of the technology.
这需要你投入大量时间去学习。
Which requires you to invest a significant amount of time in learning.
新模型、新框架、使用技术的新方式，当然，
The new model, the new framework, the new way to use the technology, which of course,
这会挤占你核心的专注工作时间。
takes away from your core focused working time.
所以这是一种恶性下降的螺旋，
So it's sort of an evil downward spiral
它真的让你觉得无法完成任何
that really prevents you from feeling like you're able to accomplish anything of.
有意义的事，只感到极度劳累、极度疲惫。
Of meaning you just feel very overworked, very tired.
我相信每一位听众
I'm confident everybody listening, uh,
都完全理解你在描述什么。
understands exactly what you're describing here.
这显然与我们先前提到的职业倦怠有关。
Uh, obviously connects to that burnout point we made earlier.
我用你文章里的另一段快速摘录来结束这个要点。
Uh, I'll close this takeaway with, uh, another quick read from your post.
你真是个了不起的作者。我真的很喜欢读你的
You're such an amazing writer. No, I love, I love reading your, uh,
那些对你所学内容的总结。
your summaries of, of what you learn.
我就念这段：AI 释放出的速度，被直接转化成了更高的期望。
So I'll just read this. The speed AI Unlocked got plowed straight back into expectations.
每一次提升都成了新的基准，
Every gain becomes a new baseline
而被要求达标的人已经喘不过气来了。
and the people expected to hit it are running out of room to breathe.
等我们讲到这一集乐观的部分时，
When we can get to the optimistic parts of this, of this episode,
也许会有些发现。
maybe we'll find something.
好，我们来聊聊带点乐观的部分。哦，对。
Okay, let's talk about which has a little bit of optimism. Oh, yeah.
好，充满了矛盾心理。
Okay. A lot of ambivalence.
对对，我先前提过这点。
Yeah, yeah, I mentioned this earlier.
这个行业无疑处于一种矛盾的状态。
The industry is definitely in a state of ambivalence.
我们试图捕捉人们现在在工作中感受到的所有情绪。
We, we try to capture all of the emotions that people are feeling at work right now.
我很高兴地报告，正如你在这里看到的，排名前两位的情绪
And I am happy to report, as you can see here, that the top two emotions.
是正面的情绪：好奇和兴奋。这太好了。
Are positive emotions, curiosity and excitement. And that's wonderful.
这很乐观，我很高兴是这样。
That is optimistic. I'm glad that's the case.
人们表示他们对这项技术感到兴奋，对
People are sharing that they're excited about the technology, about the,
它的能力、对自己能取得的成就感到兴奋。
the capabilities, about what they're able to achieve.
他们对未来可能带来什么感到好奇，
They're feeling curious about what the future might bring
也好奇随着这些模型和系统不断进化，自己还能做些什么。
and what else they could do as these models and systems continue to evolve.
所以这很好。
So that's wonderful.
但当你往下看这张榜单，你会看到
But as you go down this list, you can see
正面、负面和中性情绪有趣地交织在一起。
that there's this very interesting mix of positive, negative and neutral emotions.
人们也感到不堪重负。
People are also feeling overwhelmed.
人们感到矛盾。
People are feeling conflicted.
人们在某些方面又感到宽慰，就是关于
People are feeling relieved in certain ways, um, about, you know,
AI 从他们身上拿走了什么——在好的意义上，
what AI has taken from them in a, in a good sense, you know,
也就是他们能交给 AI 去做的事，然后人们又感到疲惫、倦怠，
what they've been able to offload to AI and then people are feeling tired, burnt out,
只是越来越拼命地工作。
just working hard and hard.
正如我们所说，不安、焦虑，然后又满怀希望。所以你可以看到，
As we said, uneasy, anxious and then hopeful. So as you can see,
这里有各种各样的情绪。
there is a wide variety of, of emotions here.
而且，真的很难弄清楚到底发生了什么。
And it's, uh, it's really tough to, to figure out what exactly is going on.
但有一件事我很想提一下，呃，
But one thing I, I definitely wanted to mention which, uh,
Nikhil Singhal 在和你的一期节目里提到过。
Nikhil Singhal mentioned in an episode with you.
我知道他是这档播客的朋友，也是产品领域一位了不起的领导者，
I know he's a friend of the pod and such an incredible leader in in products
在整个科技圈里也是如此。
and in general in in the tech community.
他谈到了一种「微笑式疲惫」。
He talks about smiling exhaustion.
我特别喜欢这个说法，因为我觉得它抓住了这种矛盾心理，
And I just love that term because I think it captures this ambivalence the,
旧那种情绪、旧那种职业倦怠是彻底阴郁的。
the old type of emotion, the old type of burnout was just completely grim.
你知道，它完全是关于这些负面情绪的，
You know, it, it's, it, it, it was all about these negative emotions
那种来自倦怠脱离和精疲力竭的情绪。
that come from disengagement and exhaustion.
而现在，当 Nikhil 谈到这种微笑式疲惫时，
Whereas now when the kill talks about finding exhaustion,
一方面，人们几乎有种重获新生的感觉，你知道，
it's about people almost feeling reborn on the one hand, you know,
我又在发布产品了，我在开发，我在用 AI 创造这些了不起的东西。
I'm shipping again, I'm building, I'm creating these incredible things with AI.
从没有过比现在更激动人心的时代。
There's never been a more exciting time.
但没有关闭键。
But there's no off switch.
没有关闭键。所以这种节奏残酷至极。
There's no off switch. And so the tempo is absolutely brutal.
规则每天都在自我改写。这是一种非常无情的，
The rules keep rewriting themselves every single day. It's a very relentless.
节奏。
Pace.
于是我们带着微笑，硬扛着这种感受到的疲惫。
And so we're smiling through that exhaustion that that we're feeling.
我觉得这比任何说法都更能抓住这种矛盾心理。
And I think that captures the ambivalence more than, than anything really.
我觉得也很值得回到你之前讲过的一个核心观点，
I think it's also good to kind of come back to one of the core points you made
就是有一半的人其实感觉自己工作非常
earlier that half of people are actually feeling very like they are working very
努力，有时可能筋疲力尽。
hard, probably exhausted at times.
但他们也真的很投入，全力以赴，呃，感觉很好，
But they're also just like really into, they're going in all in, uh, feeling good,
对事情的走向充满干劲。
energized about where things are going.
所以我觉得始终记住这一点很重要，
So I think it's important to always remember,
在我们分享这些负面因素时，要回到这一点上。
like kind of come back to that as we share all these negative elements.
其实有一大群人真的很享受这个时代，
There's actually a large group of people that are actually loving this time
而且状态非常好。
and doing super well.
我觉得在这里我最想强调的一点是，
There are, I think, more than anything, what I would like to highlight here is that,
你知道，我们太常用非黑即白的方式来看待事情了。
you know, we tend to think of things way too often in black and white terms.
我们把人要么看成满是狂热吹捧的人，要么看成，是叫 doomers 吗？
We see people as either people who are just full of hype or people who are, is it doomers?
这么说对吗？对。你懂的。对。
Would that be the right? Yeah. You know. Yeah.
或者黑子，随你怎么叫。
Or haters or whatever you want to call it.
我们在这里看到的是，就像人生中一贯那样，要我说，事情并不。
What we're seeing here is that, as always in life, if you ask me, things aren't.
简单。
Simple.
呃，在那层表象背后，在 Elena Berner 谈到的那些表演背后，
Um, behind that facade, behind the theatrics that Elena Berner discussed,
我们每个人心里在某种程度上既住着一个狂热者，也住着一个 doomer。
we all have both the height person within us and the doomer to a certain extent.
我们之间唯一的区别在于两者的比例不同，
And the only difference between us is that we have different amounts of each,
但我们不是非此即彼。
but we're not just one or the other.
这里真的充满了矛盾心理，
And there really is a ton of ambivalence and,
我只想让大家知道，这没关系，你知道，
and I just want people to know that it's okay, you know,
既感到兴奋好奇，又感到不堪重负，这没关系。
it's okay to be excited and curious, but also feel overwhelmed.
既觉得如释重负又觉得疲惫，这没关系。
It's okay to feel relieved and tired.
感到不满也没关系，即使总的来说，
It's okay to feel resentful, even if, all in all,
你对这项技术是持正面态度的。
you feel positive about the technology.
这些情绪可以在我们心里共存。这很自然。
Those emotions can coexist within us. It's very natural.
别让这种非此即彼的叙事，呃，
Don't let this narrative that you're either or, um, to,
去主导你，让你以为自己的感受有什么问题，
to dominate and to convince you that anything's wrong with how you feel
因为考虑到我们所处的时代，所有这些情绪其实都非常可以理解。
because really all of these emotions are very understandable given the times we're in.
这一点太重要了。我很喜欢你这么说。
Such an important point. I love that you said that.
好，那么下一个要点，我们在这里做的是，
Okay, so the next takeaway, what we did here is
当我们审视你发现的这种分化时，
when we were looking at this bifurcation that you found,
我们看了哪些职能岗位过得最好、哪些过得最差。
we looked at just which functions are having the best time and worst time.
我们之前提到过一点线索，结果发现有几类，
And we had a hint at this earlier and it turns out there's a couple
整体上眼下过得最差，也最不开心。
that are just overall having the worst time right now and feeling the least happy.
那我们就来聊聊这个。
So let's get into that.
对，绝对是。顺便说，我们去年也看到了这种情况。
Yeah. So definitely, definitely. And we saw this last year, by the way, as well.
我们看到设计师和研究人员是最消极的。
We are seeing that designers and researchers are the most negative.
说清楚一下我这话的意思，
And just to clarify what I mean by that,
你在这张幻灯片上可以看到，当涉及 AI 带来的身份转变时，
what you can see in the slide is that when it comes to AI identity shifts,
designers 和 researchers 在感到不稳定或被削弱方面的比例最高
designers and researchers are the highest in feeling either destabilized or
在感到疲惫、不堪重负或焦虑这类情绪上也是如此
diminished when it comes to emotions like feeling tired, overwhelmed or anxious.
researchers 和 designers，呃，位居前列
Researchers and designers, uh, lead the.
当然，是从负面意义上说
Pack in in a negative way, of course,
在担心自己的工作被 AI 取代方面，同样地
when it comes to worries about losing one's job to AI, again,
researchers 和 designers 的比例几乎高到了极限
researchers and designers are pretty much as high as one can be.
最后，说到这些 NPS
And then finally, when it comes to these NPS,
也就是人们是否愿意把自己的岗位推荐给朋友或
like scores of whether people would recommend their role to a friend or to a
同事的评分，researchers 和 designers 是最不愿意推荐别人
colleague, researchers and designers are the least likely to recommend entering
在此时进入他们这一岗位的
their role at this point.
我们之前聊过这个，我不知道这里还有多少可补充的
We talked about this earlier. I don't know how much more there is to add here.
基本上，再说一次，这并不一定意味着这个职能陷入了大麻烦
Basically, it's again, it's not that this function is in big trouble necessarily.
而是这个职能里的人现在就是这种感受
It's this is how people in that function are feeling right now.
你知道，我不客观，因为我也是 research 社区
You know, I'm not objective because I'm part of the research community
和 design 社区的一员
and the design community.
如果可以的话，我想对这个社区里的人说，我真心
If I may, I just want to tell people that in this community that I truly
也真诚地相信，我们这些角色从未像现在这样重要
and honestly believe that there has never been a more important time for our roles
去在我们打造的产品中体现出来
to manifest in the products that we build.
呃，Lenny，你和很多人聊过这个话题
Um, you've talked about this with many people, Lenny, in,
在之前的访谈里，聊到 taste、craft 这样的概念
in previous interviews about concept like taste, about concepts like craft,
还有 quality 这样的概念，我想到了像 Kari 这样的人
about concepts like quality, I'm thinking of people like Kari,
Linear 的 CEO，他把 quality 的重要性讲得非常精彩
Linear's CEO who talked so beautifully about the importance of quality
以及你如何打造产品。我还想到像，呃，呃，像，嗯
and how you build products. I'm thinking about people like, uh, uh, like, um.
我想到了 Katie Dill
Katie Dill comes to mind.
她有一次，我们围绕 taste 和美感聊了整整一场，Katie Dill，呃
She had a, we had a whole conversation around taste and beauty and Katie Dill, uh,
最近，呃，Jenny Wen，她负责设计，呃，负责
recently, uh, Jenny Wen, who leads design, uh, for, uh,
Anthropic 的 Claude，还有很多其他人都在谈 taste 的重要性
Claude at anthropic and so many other people who talk about the importance of taste.
谈判断力和设计的重要性
Of judgment of design.
所以我真心希望 designers 和 researchers 能够重振旗鼓
So I, I honestly hope that designers and researchers make a comeback
在他们对这个行业的感受上有所转变，因为行业需要他们
when it comes to how they feel about this industry because the industry needs them,
行业需要我们
the industry needs us.
所以我希望明年能看到变化
And so I hope we see a change next year.
这是对所有 designers 和 researchers 的呼吁
And this is the call to all designers and researchers to.
投身其中，做好我们的事，因为在这个时代它极其宝贵
Get in there and do our thing because it's incredibly valuable at this era.
是的，我最近有过几次专门聊设计的对话
Yeah, I've been, I've had a few conversations recently about just design
尤其是在聊，为什么设计没有成为巨大的价值增量
and in particular just why, why is design not a huge value add
和差异化优势，明明 AI 在这方面就是这么差
and differentiator today knowing AI is just so bad at it?
我们刚请来 Codex app 的负责人，聊为什么 AI
We just had the head of the Codex app on talking about why AI,
就是 AI 不擅长设计
like AI is not good at design.
你一眼就能看出这东西是 AI 设计的
And you could clearly tell AI designed this thing.
你会以为这正是设计成为巨大价值增量的时刻
And you would think this was the moment for design into become such a value add
以及企业差异化优势的时刻，看着被生产出来的这堆 AI 垃圾内容
and differentiator for companies seeing all this AI slop that's being produced.
所以我很乐观，这会显现出来，因为人们会说
So I'm, I'm optimistic that'll emerge as people are like,
我实在受够了这些千篇一律的东西
I'm so sick and tired of all these generic things.
我，我真的想做出点了不起的东西
I, I want to actually build something great.
是的
Yeah.
而且，如果我没记错的话
And moreover, if I recall correctly,
你在那场对话里谈到，AI 做设计的一些问题
you you in that conversation talked about how some of the issues around AI doing
也许是可解决的问题，但有些甚至是无法解决的
design are perhaps tractable problems, but some of them are even intractable.
我会说，或者说至少是难解决得多的
I, I would say, or definitely much, much harder to solve for.
事实仍然是，创造出令人惊叹的全新创意体验
It's still the case that creating incredible novel creative experiences not
并不是这项技术真正能胜任的
something that this technology is quite capable of.
所以我们拭目以待
So we'll see what happens.
但我真心希望设计和研究社区能扭转局面
But I, I really do hope that the design and research community turn around
明年改变他们对这个行业的看法
and change their minds about the industry next year.
是啊，兄弟，我，是啊，等不及做下一次调查了。会是什么样呢？
Yeah, man, I, yeah, can't wait to do next charity. What's it gonna be?
但如果你真去看"工作被 AI 取代"这一类
But if you actually look at the losing my job to AI bucket,
其实有一个岗位对失业更加担忧
there's actually a role that is even more worried about losing their job.
我相信那是数据分析。我们的情况其实很相似
And I believe that is data analytics. Our shades are kind of very similar.
为了让信息清晰。但这确实很有意思
To keep it, to keep the message clear. But that's really interesting.
数据分析师基本上是最担心失业的一群人。
The data, data analysts basically are the most worried about losing their job.
我觉得我们看到了非常强大的能力出现。有道理。是的。
I think we're, we're seeing incredible capabilities come out. Makes sense. Yeah.
现在有各种不同的模型可以用来做数据分析。
With the different, the different models out there to, to run data analysis.
我在研究领域也看到了同样的情况。
I'm seeing this in the research realm as well.
我想说，我们在编程方面也看到了惊人的进步。
I would suggest that we're also seeing incredible advancements in coding.
所以我原本以为工程师在某些方面的担忧会更高，但其实并没有。
So I was expecting engineering to be higher in, in, in certain places here and, and it's not.
呃，但再说一次，这不是关于 AI 客观上发展到了什么程度，
Um, but again, this isn't about the objective reality of how far AI has come in
也就是它胜任每种岗位的能力。
terms of its capabilities doing each of these roles.
这关乎的是从事这些岗位的人的真实感受，
This is about how people are feeling in these roles
而这两者之间并不是一一对应的关系。
and there isn't a 1 to 1 correlation between, between those things.
说到这个，我们来聊聊谁是最快乐的人。
Speaking of that, let's talk about who the happiest people are.
谁过得很好？谁过得最好？
Who's doing great? Who's doing best?
那么科技行业里最快乐的人，
So the happiest people in tech,
这一点在去年和今年的调查之间没有变化。
this is something that did not change between last year's survey and this year's.
依然是创始人和在小公司工作的人。
It's still founders and people who are working in smaller companies.
我确实觉得有必要说明，关于创始人这件事，
And I do feel the need to say that when it comes to founders,
就像你之前提到的那样，
to your point earlier being not that I know,
当创始人是一份极具挑战性、
but being a founder is an incredibly challenging,
需要投入一切的工作，这里存在一定的选择偏差，因为
all encompassing job and there is a certain selection bias here in the sense
这些人都是……
that these are people who are.
目前仍在积极担任创始人角色、
Currently in the active role of a founder in a startup that is,
公司还在运营的人，而不是那些不得不关掉创业公司的创始人。
is still running rather than founders who had to shut down their startup or whatever it might be.
所以我只是想说清楚我们看的是哪一群人。
So I just want to make that clear around who we're looking at.
但是，是的，当我们看创始人，以及在这里看
But, but yes, when we look at founders and when we look at, in this case,
呃，也看公司规模的时候，
if you're looking at, um, company size as well,
你会发现，无论是乐观程度，还是呃……
you can see that whether it's optimism, whether it's, uh, uh.
职业倦怠、裁员担忧，还是人们是否愿意推荐自己的工作。
Burnout layoff worry or whether people would recommend their job.
呃，你会看到这些指标有升有降，取决于
Uh, you're seeing these, these, uh, increases or decreases depending on,
具体的问题。
on the question.
非常明显，创始人在几乎每一项指标上都名列前茅。
It's very clear that founders are top of nearly every measure.
他们的乐观比例达到 71%。
They're 71% optimistic.
他们最享受自己的工作，倦怠程度最低，
They're enjoying their jobs the most. They have the lowest burnout,
对裁员的担忧最少，对 AI 最兴奋。
the lowest layoff worry, the most AI excitement.
和我们看到的其他效应相比，这是个中等强度的效应，呃，
It's a it's a medium sized effect compared to other effects we saw, um,
但非常显著。
but very significant.
话虽如此，你知道，如果我们谈创始人，
And, and that said, you know, if we talk about founders,
即便拥有那种所有权和自主权，也是有极限的。
even having that ownership and even having that agency has its limits.
呃，创始人依然，呃，你懂的，
Um, founders are still, uh, you know,
很多创始人仍然处于中等或至少中等程度的倦怠，47% 的创始人
many founders are still moderately or at least moderately burnt out 47% of founders
是这样，呃，就像我们之前说的，
that would be um and as we said earlier,
即便是创始人，也不太可能建议别人去当创始人。
even founders aren't very likely to recommend being a founder to other people.
尤其是现在，这很有意思。
Right now, which is very interesting.
我觉得还有一点很重要，呃，肯定存在，就像你说的，
I think it's also important to note, uh, there's definitely this, as you said,
那种「从没有比现在更适合创业的时候」的梗。
this kind of a meme of there's never been a better time to build.
人们可能看到这个就想，我得开个公司。这是最好的位置。
People may see this and be like, I gotta start a company. It's the best place to be.
可能正是当下这一刻，人们对此感到最兴奋。
It may be this moment currently where people are feeling most excited about it.
然后随着泡沫，你知道，我不确定这是不是泡沫，
And then as the bubble, you know, I don't know if it's a bubble,
但当情况开始变难时，这种情绪可能会转变。
but as things start to get harder, there may be a shift away from that.
到目前为止很有意思，我们连续两年看到创始人是最快乐的。
So this so far, interesting that we've seen two years in a row founders are the happiest.
但我在想这会不会改变，如果市场变了，如果，你知道，
But I wonder if that changes, if the market changes, if some, you know,
诸如此类的情况。
that kind of thing.
所以这并不是说你当了创始人就会快乐。
So this isn't saying you're going to be happy if you become a founder.
但真的很有意思，连续两年，在所有那些最
But it is really interesting that two years in a row of all of the like the most
清晰的结论中，最清晰的结论之一就是创始人在
clear, one of the clearest takeaways is just founders seem to be happiest across
每个维度上似乎都是最快乐的。
every dimension.
是的。还有公司规模也是。再说一次，
Yeah. And then company size as well. Again,
如果你在更大的公司工作，乐观程度会下降。
optimism goes down if you're working for a larger company.
呃，如果你在更大的公司工作，你会更容易倦怠。
Um, you get more burnt out if you're working for a larger company.
如果你在更大的公司工作，你会更担心裁员，
You're more worried about layoffs if you're working for a larger company
而且如果你在更大的公司工作，你也更不愿意推荐自己的岗位。
and you're less likely to recommend your role if you're working for a larger company.
所以这一点也保持一致。
So that also remained consistent.
如果我们只看职业倦怠这一项，
And if we look just at burnout specifically,
你可以很清楚地看到
then you can see very clearly here
从在一到十人的小型初创公司工作，
that burnout climbs in very significant ways in between working for a small one to
到在五千或一万人的大型企业工作，倦怠感显著上升。
10 person startup and working for a 5,000 or 10,000 person enterprise company.
太夸张了。它的线性程度太惊人了，几乎没有任何波动。
It's so wild. It's wild how linear this is. Like there's no bump.
而末尾那两个数据，就像你在图表里指出的，
And then those two at the end there, as you point out here in the chart there,
是在误差范围之内的。
it's within margin of error.
是的，是的。太夸张了，一直在往上走。
Yeah, yeah. It's like wild here, just like only goes up.
并没有一个最佳点，然后再降下来。
There's not like a sweet spot and then it comes down again.
如果你回到之前那一张图，也是完全一样的情况。
And then if you go back to the previous start, exactly the same thing.
就是非常线性的。一切都在上升，变得更糟，
It's just like very linear. Everything goes up and gets worse
随着你所在公司规模的增大。
as your company size groups.
太夸张了。
That's wild.
没错。我想强调一点，比如就拿倦怠来说。
Absolutely. I would say one thing to highlight here, like if you look at burnout, for example.
就是即便是最低的，也仍然相当高。对吧。
Is that even the, the, the lowest is still fairly high. Right.
所以我会说，人们感觉倦怠稍微少一些，稍微健康一些，
So I would say people are feeling somewhat less burnt out, somewhat healthier,
是在初创公司工作的时候。
working for a starter.
但我会认为，这种程度的倦怠和担忧，是令人担心的。
But I, I would view these levels of burnout, of worry as, uh, as worrisome.
我很担心现在科技行业里这种担忧的程度。氛围不太好。
I'm worried about the level of worry right now in in tech. It is not a good vibe.
你提到我们十年前在 Airbnb 相识。
You know, you mentioned how we met a decade ago at Airbnb.
我确实觉得那时候科技行业的氛围很不一样。
I do feel like the vibe was very different then in in tech.
所以我对这里看到的数据有点担忧。
So I am a bit concerned about the numbers that we're seeing here.
但没错，从相对的角度来看，
But yes, from a relative sense, a relative point of view, um,
也许人们应该考虑做出转变，
perhaps one should consider doing a shift
去创业，或者去更小的公司工作。
and starting your own thing or working for a smaller company.
是的，没错。这也是其中一个要点。
Yeah, exactly. And that'll be one of the takeaways.
你知道，如果我们能为非科技行业也做一次这样的调查就太棒了。
You know, it would be awesome if we do one of these for non tech.
我真的很好奇，就像你说科技行业的人感到恐惧和担忧。
I'm really curious, just like you think people are feel scared and worried in tech.
我很好奇这和比如蓝领群体相比会怎样。
I'm so curious how that would compare to, you know, like say the blue collar.
或者其他职能岗位，我不确定我们有没有相应的受众去做这个，
Folks or other functions like I, I don't know if we have the audience to do that,
但那会很有意思。
but that'd be really interesting.
我是说，我觉得我的 HVAC 技师现在对自己的职业感觉挺不错的。
I mean, I think my HVAC technician is feeling pretty great about his career right now.
佛罗里达热得要命。
Burning hot in Florida.
每个人都需要空调。这在短期内不会改变。
Everyone needs air conditioning. That's not going to change anytime soon.
所以，是的，如果你想听我们的结论，我们应该转行去做 HVAC，开个公司。
So, yeah, if you want our takeaways, we should get it to HVAC and start a company.
我们真该这么干。开个水管工生意。哦，天哪。
We should do that. Start a plumbing business. Oh, man.
我喜欢这次调查的一点是，我们再次做这个调查，
So what I love about this, doing the survey again,
我们开始发现一些始终成立的结论，
as we're starting to find things that are consistently true,
下一个要点又是一个很好的例子，
and the next takeaway is another really good example
去年我们也看到过，是关于管理者的。
that we saw last year too around managers.
我们来聊聊这个。
Let's get into that.
是的，我是说，也许人们已经意识到这一点了。
Yeah, so I mean, perhaps people are aware of this.
管理者非常重要。你的管理者是谁，可能比你岗位的大多数其他
Managers matter a turn. Who your manager is probably matters more than most other
特征都更重要。
characteristics of your role.
我们去年非常明确地发现了这一点，今年又一次。
And we found this very explicitly last year and this year again. Um,
管理者的有效性。
manager effectiveness.
所以我们基本上是问大家，你的管理者有多称职？
So we basically asked people, how effective is your manager?
你会如何评价你的管理者？
How would you rate your manager?
你在这里可以看到，你的管理者越称职，
And what you can see here is that the more effective your manager is,
你感到的倦怠就越少，也越喜欢自己的工作。
the less burnt out you feel and the more you enjoy your job.
我们看到的这个影响是非常非常巨大的。
And this is a massive, massive effect that we're seeing.
比如说，如果你有一位极其称职的管理者，
So if you have an extremely effective manager, for example,
你报告的工作愉悦度会高出约 65%，
you're reporting around 65% higher job enjoyment
而且倦怠感也大幅降低。
and DRAM mathematically lower burnout.
问题在于，供给方面，
The problem is, is the, the supply, um,
只有约 25% 的受访者认为他们的管理者非常称职，
only about 25% of the sample rates their manager as highly effective
而 36% 的受访者认为他们的管理者不称职，
and 36% of the sample rated their managers as ineffective,
顺便说一句，这和去年相比变化很小。
which by the way is a very small change from from last year.
所以我们看到管理者得到的评价并不太好。
So we're seeing managers be rated not so well.
与此同时，我们发现当管理者称职时，
And at the same time, we're seeing that when managers are effective,
尽管这显然不够频繁，它对人们的工作满足感、
which is clearly not often enough, the impact that has on people's enjoyment,
职业倦怠以及其他方面的影响都令人惊叹。
burnout and other aspects as well is incredible.
太不可思议了。
That's wild.
我觉得我们在这里为世界带来了新的洞见。
Like, like, I think we're adding new insight into the world here.
我发现这一点是我从未见过的。
Just finding this like I've never, never seen this before.
管理者的影响力有多大，我们总是听到一些坊间说法，比如，
Just how impactful managers that we always hear anecdotes, we always hear like,
人们离职，不是离开工作，而是离开他们的管理者。
you know, people only leave, they don't leave jobs, they leave their manager.
但这种影响之大真是令人吃惊。
But this is wild just how much that impacts you.
显然，一个可能的启示是，如果你过得不好，
And clearly, one of the takeaways might be go if you're having a bad time,
就去找一个更好的管理者。
find a better manager.
是啊，说起来容易做起来难。
Yeah. Easier said than done.
是的，但在继续之前，
Yeah, but there's a couple of things here I want to I want to also note
我还想指出几点。
before we move on.
首先，我们正处于“大扁平化”时代。
First of all, we are in the era of the Great Flattening.
我们正处于“创始人模式”时代。
We're in the era of founder mode.
现在人们管理的直接下属比以往任何时候都多。
People have more direct reports now than ever before.
我们在尽量保持组织扁平，去除层级。
Um, we're trying to keep things as flat this possible and remove hierarchy.
我对此有些担忧。我觉得，
I'm concerned about this. I think, um,
显然扁平化和减少层级有其充分的理由。
obviously there are good arguments for a flatness and lack of hierarchy.
但考虑到你的管理者对你的幸福感有多重要，
Um, but I am just to see where this goes given the importance of who your manager is
我很好奇这会走向何方。
on your well being.
第二点是，我们之前谈到过工作过度，
And then the second thing is we talked earlier about being overworked,
谈到 AI 给我们带来的挤压。
about this squeeze that AI has on us.
谁是最能左右这种挤压的人呢？
Who's the person more than anyone else who kind of manages that squeeze?
是你的管理者，对吧？是他在保护你。
It's your manager, right? It's your manager who protects you.
在很多方面，几乎是你的管理者决定了
It's your manager who in many ways almost dictates, uh,
你会不会被过度加班。
how much you may be overworked or not.
所以，是的，这比以往任何时候都更重要。
And so, yeah, this, this matters more than ever before.
我确实担心，我们看到的一些负面现象是
I'm definitely concerned that some of the negative phenomenon we're seeing are a
我们对科技行业管理者所做之事的结果，
function of what we're doing to managers in tech
也是我们组织架构搭建方式的结果。
and how we're building out our organizations.
这个观点太有意思了。
Such an interesting point.
无论现在还是下次，
We whether we do it now or next time,
看看这些针对管理者的指标，比如他们倦怠程度高多少，
just looking at these metrics for managers like how much more burned out are they,
幸福感和乐观程度低多少，都会很有意思。
how much less happy and optimistic are they, would be really interesting.
在原帖里有几处我想强调的地方，
There's a couple of notes here in the actual post that I want to highlight
我觉得非常有意思。
that I thought are really interesting.
一个核心结论是，提升公司留存率最大的杠杆
One is just core takeaway here is the biggest lever you have to increase retention
就是提升你的管理者，把人安排好，
in your company is improve your managers, put people on,
基本上就是给人们配更好的管理者。
but connect people better managers basically.
太有意思了。这是你实实在在能做的事。
So interesting. That's like a thing you can do.
当然，说起来容易做起来难，
Obviously, easier said than done,
但那是你能改变的最大杠杆。
but that's the biggest lever of things you can change.
你还提到的另一点是，评分最差的管理者集中在数据/
And then the other thing you noted is the worst rated managers cluster in data slash
分析和设计领域。
analytics and design.
可怜的设计。
Poor design.
是的，我不确定对此有没有明确的解释。
Yes. And I'm not sure there's a clear explanation, uh, for that.
我觉得一个可能的解释是，还是那句话，
Um, I think one possible explanation is that, again, you know,
管理者也只是普通人。
managers are just people, too.
所以设计管理者、数据和分析管理者，
And so design managers and data and analytic managers are,
从我们看到的数据来看，设计和分析领域的人明显过得很煎熬。
are in design and in analytics, they are suffering clearly based on what we saw.
我觉得很难把你在科技行业的感受与你作为管理者的工作分开。
And I think it's hard to separate how you feel in tech from your job as a manager.
很难不把一些负面情绪转嫁到你的团队
It's hard not to put some of your negative energy onto your team
和与你共事的人身上。
and the people you work with.
所以我对设计管理者、
And and so I have a lot of, I have a lot of empathy for design managers,
研究管理者、数据和分析管理者，
research managers, data and analytics managers
以及其他此刻正处境艰难、
and other managers in tech who are having a hard time right now
提不起劲的科技行业管理者深感理解。
and they're not feeling energized.
不幸的是，这些情绪有一部分被转嫁到了他们的直接下属身上。
And unfortunately, some of that is being pushed on to their direct reports.
然后，我非常感激在我工作过的一些公司里
And then, and then I very much appreciate in some of the companies I've worked for
有机会接受管理者培训
having the opportunity to go through manager training,
我觉得这在很多组织里还是太少见了
which is something that's still all too rare, I feel, within organizations.
如果你在听这段内容，而且你是组织里的领导者
If you're listening to this and your leader in an organization,
如果你是公司的高管，请多投入在你的管理者身上
if your C suite at a company, please invest more in your managers.
如果你现在正在找工作
And if you're looking for a job right now,
请认真考虑你的经理会是谁
consider carefully who your manager might be
因为可能没有什么比这个人是谁
because probably nothing will have more impact on your well being than who
更能影响你的幸福感了
that person ends up being.
再补充一点公司现在的处境有多艰难
And to build on how difficult things are for companies right now,
挖角的程度、抛出的高薪offer之激烈
the level of poaching and offers throwing out, thrown out at the best,
想象一下这有多糟：好不容易找到一位优秀的管理者
people just imagine how sucky it is to find a great manager,
把人培养成出色的管理者
train people to become awesome managers.
结果却眼睁睁把他们失去，失去给
And then they get, you know, only to lose them, only to lose them to, you know,
那些实验室，那些有无限资金的人
the Labs, people with infinite money.
所以这格外艰难，正好引出我们最后的结论
So it's just extra hard, which is a good segue to our final takeaway,
它很好地总结了大家现在的真实感受
which is a really good summary of just what is what people are feeling right now.
是啊，这是史上最疯狂的时候
Yeah, it is the. The wildest it's ever been.
我们请大家描述科技行业当下的状态
We asked people to describe the state of the tech industry right now.
我们收到了成千上万条
We got thousands of.
回复。这些基本都是开放式回答
Responses. These were essentially open ended responses
我们把这些描述聚合成了这个词云
and we just sort of clustered those descriptions into this, uh, this word cloud.
我仍然很喜欢词云，有些研究者是反词云派的
I still love word cloud. Some researchers are sort of anti word cloud.
我很喜欢，我不会为用词云道歉。不，这太棒了
I love, I'm not gonna apologize for the word cloud. No, this is amazing.
它太清晰了，看看这个，就看看这个
It's like such a clear. Look at this. Just look at this.
这正是那种感觉
This is exactly what it feels.
是的，我们看到变化，看到混乱，看到速度
Yeah. We're seeing change. We're seeing chaos. We're seeing speed.
我们看到兴奋、动荡、炒作、缺乏稳定、可能的泡沫
We're seeing excitement, flux, hype, a lack of stability, a potential bubble,
但也有疯狂的机会
but also crazy opportunities.
一切都在演变，一切都不稳定
Everything's evolving. Everything's unstable.
它有代价，更好、更糟、巨大、令人困惑
It comes with costs. It's better, it's worse, it's huge. It's confusing.
全都揉在一起，形成一个前所未有地混乱的行业
All smushed together into a more chaotic industry than it's ever been.
呃，我完全不懂棒球，也可能是板球
Um, I don't understand anything about baseball. Or maybe it's cricket.
但我们收到了这句话，你懂吗？
But we got this quote, do you understand?
懂棒球的话，希望看这段的你能明白这些
Baseball does. Hopefully if you're watching, you understand these things.
我们收到这句话：我们正处于一场巨大变革的第二局
But we got this quote, we're in the second inning of a massive shift.
没人知道结局会怎样，你能做的就是不断上场击球
No one knows how it will end, but all you can do is keep taking at bats.
那是板球还是棒球的说法？我不确定，那是棒球
Is that a cricket thing or baseball? I don't know. That's baseball.
我觉得，我不知道有多少局
I think it's, I don't know how many innings.
我不知道板球里有没有局，但这肯定是棒球
I don't know if there's innings in cricket, but it's definitely baseball.
至少用在棒球上说得通。基本就是说要不断尝试
It works for baseball at least. Yeah. Basically just saying keep trying.
就不断出手、不断射门
Just keep taking, taking shots, shots on goal.
是啊，好多精彩的引言
Yeah, yeah. So many good quotes.
我这里还看到一句很不错的：科技行业很躁狂
Another one I see here, which was, which was good one tech is manic,
一半人脱离现实，紧抓潮流，一头扎进过度炒作
half out of touch, clinging to the bandwagon, pouring into the over hype.
另一半人被前一半人累坏了。这来自一位资深PM
The other half are exhausted by the first half. That came from a senior PM.
呃，是啊，很有意思，整体来看这太疯狂了
Um, yeah, fa fascinating stuff when we look at this overall it's crazy.
看，我们又看到这种分化：在我们做情感分析时
See how we see again this bifurcation that 37% of the words used
有37%的用词是正面的
when we ran sentiment analysis were positive,
37%是负面的，剩下约26%是中性的
37% were negative and the the remaining 26% or so were neutral.
基本上是对半分
Basically an even split.
我们都在看同样的事，但一半人觉得激动人心
We're all seeing the same thing. But half of us find it thrilling.
另一半人觉得可怕
The other half find it terrifying.
我看到这些数据时相当吃惊
I was, I was, you know, rather taken aback when I, when I saw these data.
我们分得如此对等，真是不可思议
It's pretty wild how equally divided we are.
是啊，兄弟
Yeah, man.
呃，我想我前面用过这句话
And, uh, I think use this quote earlier
就是：现在已经是往后最"正常"的时候了
that this is the most normal it's ever gonna be.
我是说，我也说不准
I mean, I don't know.
呃，预言是给傻瓜的，所以我不会试着去当先知
Um, the prophecy was given to the fool, so I'm not gonna try and be a, be a prophet.
但是，嗯，是的，我，我觉得它不太可能变得，你知道，
But, um, yes, I, I doubt it's gonna get, you know,
从统计上比现在更正常、更常态化，所以。
more normal and normalized statistically than, than this, so.
我想，我们只能，只能拭目以待了。
We'll, we'll, we'll wait and see, I guess.
是的。
Yeah.
呃，如果放眼来看，我们正在见证历史，
Uh, like if we zoom out, we're living through history right now,
这种变化的规模，是前所未有的。
the amount of change and, like, this is unprecedented.
你知道，人们总用工业革命来做比喻，
You know, the industrial revolution is always the metaphor people use,
这很贴切，呃，也许很疯狂，也许不然。
which is accurate, uh, maybe crazy or maybe not.
但这，这就是有趣之处，就像，
But it's, that's the interesting part, like,
生活在这样一个时代是多么有趣。
what an interesting time to be living through.
Elon 有一种非常有趣的描述方式，
Elon had this really interesting way of describing it,
说如果我们此刻还活着，我们肯定是生活在模拟世界里，
like we're definitely living in a simulation if we're if we're alive right now
就在我们即将开始在太空建数据中心，而 AI 即将变得
when we're about to start building data centers in space and AI is going to be
和人脑一样聪明的时候。
as smart as human brains.
你恰好在那一刻活着的概率有多大？
Like what are the chances you are alive at that moment?
这大概说得通，也许某种更高级的智能正在模拟历史上最
Which is probably okay, maybe some higher intelligence is simulating the most
有趣的时代。我不知道这是好是坏。
interesting time in history. I don't know if that's good or bad.
但听着，听着，我非常尊敬，呃，Elon。
But listen, listen, I have a lot of respect for, for, uh, Elon.
嗯，像 Elon 这样的人选择关注宇宙以及那里的一切，
Um, people like Elon have chosen to focus on the universe and what's out there
以及支配宇宙的法则。
and the laws that govern the universe.
那是他们的关注点。
And that's their focus.
至少从学术训练上说，我成了一名心理学家，
I became a psychologist by academic training, at least,
因为我一直以来关注的都是人。
because my focus has always been on people.
如果要用一个总结性的想法来收尾这项研究，
And if I had to share a closing thought to wrap up all of this research,
我会说，拥有最先进的 AI，
I would say that having the most advanced AI
以及能用上世界上最好的模型，并不会。
and the access to the best models in the world won't.
并不能决定。
Won't determine.
你的组织是否会成功，
Whether your organization succeeds,
我们必须记住，这一切的背后都是人，是人。
we have to remember that underlying all of this stuff are people, people.
作为人，我们正在经历人生中最巨大的转变和变化，
We as people are going through the most massive shift and changes
从未有过的巨变。
that we ever have in our lives.
是人在感到兴奋、疲惫、充满希望又害怕，
And it's people who are feeling excited and exhausted and hopeful and scared,
常常同时涌现。
often all at once.
我们都在参与塑造和构建这个未来，
And we're all taking part in crafting and building this future
我们希望几年后这个未来里仍有我们的一席之地。
that we hope still has a place for us in a few years.
所以我一直把这一点记在心里。
And so I keep that in mind all the time.
是人在推动这些创新。
It's people driving these innovations.
是了不起的人在打造这些技术。我的关注点永远都在人身上。
It's incredible people building these technologies. My focus will always be on, on the people.
我希望，如果你正在看这个视频，请照顾好自己。
And I hope that if you're out there watching this, you take care of yourself.
走出去接触真实生活，花点时间反思你在职业中真正想要什么，
You touch grass, you take a moment to reflect on what you want for yourself in in
再次记住，产生所有这些情绪都是正常的，
your career and you remember again that it's fine to feel all of the emotions
你应该做任何对自己有用的事，来熬过科技行业这段疯狂的时期。
and you should just do whatever works for you to get through this wild period in the
所以差不多是这样。
tech industry. So kind of.
接着这个话题，你花了很多时间去思考这些结果，
Building on that you, you spend a lot of time thinking through the results
以及人们究竟能用这些数据做什么，因为只是报告出来是一回事，
and what people can actually do with this data because it's one thing to just report,
说“这是人们的感受”。
here's what people are feeling.
好的，很好。呃，那人们该怎么做？
Okay, cool. Uh, what should people do?
所以报告的末尾有一个非常重要的部分，呃，
So there's a really important section at the end of the report that, uh,
我们应该花点时间来聊聊，那就是——什么？
that we should spend a little time on, which is just what?
我们接下来该往哪里走？
Where do we go from here?
这告诉我们应该做些什么，
What does this tell us we should be doing,
如果我们能做点什么，让自己基本上走向一个更快乐的状态。
if we could do anything to kind of move ourselves basically into a happier place.
那么先从员工说起，你知道，
So starting with if you're an employee, you know,
尤其如果你是公司里的一名 IC（个人贡献者），我们观察到的一点是，
especially if you're an IC working at a company, one thing we saw,
那些感到被赋能、充满干劲的人反映的是，
people who feel amplif fight and energized reporting is
他们其实是深入钻研具体的任务和要完成的具体工作，
that they actually went deep on specific tasks and specific jobs to be done
而不是试图做一个什么都干的通才。
rather than trying to be the generalist who does everything.
我认为正是那些试图，
I think it's the people who try.
想做通才，或者过于偏向做通才的人，最终会严重职业倦怠，对吧。
To be or, or lean too much into being a generalist who end up getting severely burnt out, right.
所以我想稍微提醒大家，不要太受那些说法的影响。
And so I just want to caution people a little bit away from the narratives
认为现在必须成为通才，什么都要做
that you need to be a generalist at this point and just do all of the things
完全忽视自己岗位的核心职责
and completely ignore the core parts of your role.
我觉得这是非常糟糕的主意
I think that's a bad, bad idea.
而且根据大家反馈的情况
And based on what people are reporting it,
这至少不会让你感觉良好
it's not going to end up with you at least feeling good.
好的
Good, right.
我也希望大家警惕这种挤压
Um, I also would love for people to watch out for this squeeze,
也就是同样的薪水却干更多的活
being overworked for the same pay.
我们值得更好的对待。我们在文中附上了一个职业倦怠测试，去做一下
We deserve better. We've LinkedIn the article to a burnout test. Take the test.
看看你在倦怠量表上的位置，然后基于此
See where you're at on the burnout scale and then, you know, based on that,
反思自己的处境，和经理沟通，重新梳理你的工作范围
reflect on where you are, talk to your manager, scope out your work again, you know,
重新校准，和经理就工作重新达成一致，确保
recalibrate, realign with your manager on your work and make sure
你不会被挤出
that you're not being, uh, squeezed out of.
挤出那种对工作抱有积极态度
Of, uh, you know, being positive about,
以及在岗位上取得成功的状态
about your role and being successful in your role.
在你梳理这份清单时
Um, as you're going through this list,
我先确保大家完全理解我们的框架
let me just make sure people fully understand the frame that were
因为你分成了两大类
because you made these two buckets,
基本上就是基于这个结果你能做的事
basically things you you can do based on this result.
一类是如果你是员工，我想有五条建议
One is just if you're an employee, I think you have five pieces of advice.
如果你是公司，也有大约五条建议
If you're a company, you have five ish pieces of advice.
说得非常清楚些，第一条就是挑选几件你希望 AI
So just to be super clear, the first one is just pick a couple things you want AI to
派上用场的事，然后在这几件事上深入钻研，而不是四处铺开
be useful for and just go deep on those couple things versus trying to spread it all
让 AI 帮你做所有事
around and AI has to be doing everything for you.
挑几件你最感兴趣的事
Pick a couple things that you're most excited.
然后在那上面真正深入。另一条就是你说的
About and then just go really deep there. The other is this what you said?
警惕这种挤压，注意自己是否被压榨，然后和经理谈，嘿
Just watch the squeeze, watch you being squeezed and talk to your manager about, hey,
我的工作范围增加了，薪酬却没变，诸如此类
my scope's increased, nothing's changed comp wise, that kind of.
完全正确
Absolutely.
再说到经理
And then speak of managers, again,
第三点是，在你对工作的感受上，经理显然比几乎任何
the third point is that your manager clearly matters more than pretty much anything
其他因素都更重要
else when it comes to how you feel about work.
保护好这段关系，投入这段关系
Protect that relationship. Invest in that relationship.
和经理建立良好的沟通渠道
Build up good communication lines with your manager.
学会更好地向上管理。这种在
Learn to manage up better. That investment in
关系上的投入，会在你的感受上得到极大回报
that relationship will pay off greatly in terms of how you feel.
除此之外，首先
And then beyond that, first of all,
如果你想尝试在更小的公司工作，或者自己创业
if you want to try out working for a smaller company or starting your own company,
这显然有一些好处，所以值得考虑
clearly there are some advantages to that, and so it might be worth considering.
然后如果你处于职业生涯早期
And then if you're earlier in your career
感觉晋升阶梯的横档在慢慢消失
and you feel like the rungs of the ladder are slowly disappearing
往上爬变得越来越难
and it's becoming harder to climb that ladder, um,
我非常相信导师制以及它的价值
I'm a huge believer in mentorship and the value of mentorship.
强有力的导师指导仍然极其有效
Strong mentorship is still incredibly effective thing.
去寻找这样的团队、这样的经理
Seek the teams, seek the managers,
寻找那些愿意投入精力培养你的人
seek the people who are willing to invest in developing you.
这非常有价值，尤其是在这个时代
Um, it's incredibly valuable, especially in this era.
这就是我们给员工的建议
So that's what we have for employees.
如果你在带领团队、在管理公司，那么同样地
And then if you're leading a team, if you're leading a company, then again,
正如我们之前提到的，投入培养你的经理
as we mentioned before, invest in your managers.
这大概是你能花的最值得的钱之一
It's probably some of the best money you'll ever, ever spend.
让我难过的是，我们样本中只有四分之一
It's, it's sad to me that only a quarter of our sample
或许整个科技从业者群体也是如此，认为自己的经理非常高效
and perhaps tech workers in general rate their manager as highly effective.
在我看来这是一个非常大的危险信号，是科技行业的一大问题
That to me is a major, major red flag. It's a major issue in tech.
所以如果你想改善职业倦怠，想提升工作满意度
And so if you want to improve burnout, if you want to elevate enjoyment,
想在这些来自 AI 实验室的疯狂 offer 满天飞时提高留存率
if you want to improve retention with these crazy job offers flying around from,
你就必须投入培养你的经理
from AI labs, you have to invest in your managers.
此外还要管理好这种挤压。大家感受到 AI 正在抬高
Um, and then otherwise manage that squeeze. People are feeling how AI is raising.
标准，而且是以不可持续的方式
Bars in ways that aren't sustainable,
所以你必须找到合适的期望水平
so you have to figure out the right level of expectations
以及合适的生产力水平。
and the right level of productivity.
呃，别让阶梯最底层的那一级腐烂掉。
Um, don't let that bottom rung of the ladder rot.
你要确保为入门级员工做好该做的事，
You know, make sure that you're doing what you need to for entry level people to
让他们能晋升，因为这些职业早期的人可能也是你能找到的最 AI
advance because those early career people are also probably some of the most AI
原生的一群人，对吧？他们觉得用这些技术非常自然。
native people you can find, right? They find it very natural.
使用这些技术，某种程度上比那些已经，你懂的，
To use these technologies, in some ways more so than people who have been, you know,
太习惯于旧范式的人更自然。
too used to previous paradigms.
然后私心里，我希望领导者能多关注一点设计、
So and then selfishly, I hope that leaders pay a little bit more attention to design
研究以及其他比别的岗位感受更负面的角色。
and research and other roles who are feeling more negative than other roles.
也要记住，这项技术，
And keep in mind that this technology,
AI 在托举一些人，同时也在动摇另一些人。
AI is lifting some people and destabilizing others.
你真的必须关注这一点。
And you really have to pay attention to that.
我们显然没有以相同的方式体验这项技术。
We are clearly not experiencing this technology in the same way.
很棒的收获。
Amazing takeaways.
我想再强调一下你提到的那个职业倦怠调查。
I want to double down on that burnout survey that you, um, that you mentioned.
我想说，我们会在节目说明里放上链接，
I want to make, we're going to link to it in the show notes,
但其实有人会觉得这听起来很傻，
but it actually people have set like it sounds like dumb
“我为什么要去做这个？”
and why am I going to do that?
我确实经历过好几段倦怠期，却没有意识到
I've like, I've definitely gone through periods of burnout and wasn't aware that
这件事正在发生。
that was was happening.
意识到“哦，哇，我现在这种感觉并不正常”真的很有帮助。
And it's so helpful to like, oh, wow, this is not normal what I'm feeling right now.
知道这一点，其实没关系，你现在只是极度倦怠。
And knowing this, that you're okay, you're extremely burnt out right now.
然后你就可以决定该怎么处理这个信息。
You, you, then you can decide what you want to do with that information.
通常就是，你懂的，找教练聊聊，跟你的经理谈谈，
Often it's, you know, talk to a coach, talk to your manager,
如果可以的话就休息一段时间。
take some time off if you can.
但仅仅知道这一点其实就很有力量，
But just knowing that is actually really powerful
而且你基于真实的科学和研究做了一个非常棒的测验，
and you made this really great quiz based on actual science and research that
我们会放上它的链接。
that that will link to.
百分之百太棒了。
Hundred percent awesome.
那么，呃，还有什么我们没聊到的吗？
Now, um, is there anything else that we haven't talked about?
还有什么想留给大家的话吗？
Anything else you want to leave folks with?
我们聊了很多，所以我不确定是否还有遗漏。
We've covered a lot, so I don't know if there's anything left.
我们当然会附上报告的链接，让大家能深入了解。
We'll obviously link them to the report where they can go deeper.
我们还会根据这次对话得出的内容做一期后续，
We're also going to do a follow up based on what comes out of this conversation,
以及我们在评论里看到的东西，因为这里信息量很大，还有很多，呃，
what we see in the comments because this is a lot of information and a lot of, uh,
吓人的东西，也有一些乐观的东西。
scary stuff, some optimistic stuff.
呃，我们没法，你懂的，我们不会对每件事都有答案，
Um, we can't, you know, we're not going to have answers to everything,
但我们打算做一期后续，就讲讲“这些是浮现出来的问题”。
but we're planning to do a follow up of just here's what came up.
看看我们能不能找到一些答案。
Let's see if we can find any answers.
但除此之外，你还有什么想分享的吗？
But other than that, is there anything else that you want to share?
有一个有趣的现象我想提一下。呃，
There's one interesting phenomenon that I wanted to to mention. Um,
我们开始看到这种情况。
we're starting to see this.
AI 负罪感，尤其是在职业早期的人当中，意思是
AI guilt and in particular amongst people who are early in their career in the sense
职业早期的人觉得，利用这项技术
that people who are early in their career feel like leveraging the technology is a
某种程度上有点像作弊，而这种负罪感会随着资历增长而减弱。
little bit like cheating in a sense, and that guilt declines with seniority.
呃，特别是，我们看到做产品营销以及数据与分析的人，
Um, and in particular, we're seeing people in actually product marketing and data and analytics.
这在之前几个地方也出现过，感受到的负罪感最强。
Which showed up previously in a couple of places, feeding the most guilt.
呃，这和众所周知、早已确立的冒充者现象有关，对吧？
Um, this is related to the well known and well established imposter phenomenon, right?
就是那种“我不够好”。
Like, I'm not good enough.
呃，有能力的人觉得自己的成功并不真正属于自己，
Um, competent people feeling like their success isn't really theirs,
而是别人的功劳，只不过这一次我们把它归到了 AI 身上，
it's someone else's, except this time we're putting that's on AI,
归到一项技术上，而不是其他人身上。
on a technology rather than other people.
我想对所有可能有这种负罪感的人说，
I would say to all of you who might be feeling that guilt,
AI 是一项了不起的技术。
AI is an incredible technology.
好好用它。学会怎么用它。我觉得它不会消失。
Leverage it. Learn how to leverage it. I doubt it's going away.
它今天是它最差的样子了，只会越来越好。
It's the worst it's ever going to be today. It's only getting better.
所以完全没有理由为使用它而感到负罪。
So there's no, no reason to feel guilty about leveraging it on.
恰恰相反，我觉得我们不可避免地一直都在用它。所以。
On the contrary, I think inevitably we all are all the time. So.
那么，作为结束语，我只想向你表示感谢。
Well, to close note, I just want to appreciate you.
你在这里所做的工作非常了不起，还有那些
It's incredible the work that you've done here and the work
在这么多次调查中我们一起完成的。
that we've done together over the many surveys.
这就像是你和我一起做的一件副业。
It's just like, it's like a side thing you do with me.
运营着，怎么说呢，这个领域最大的调查之一，
Running like, I don't know, one of the biggest surveys out there around this stuff,
也许是最大的，分析它，把它写得如此精彩。
maybe the biggest, analyzing it, writing it so beautifully.
所以我觉得这是一份非常独特而特别的报告。
So I think this is a really unique and special report.
我很感激你和我一起做这件事。
And I appreciate you for doing this with me.
我真的很高兴这一切的走向，还有，
It's I'm really, I'm really happy about where this all goes and, and just the,
我们为大家所做的事情。
what we're doing for folks.
非常非常感谢你。
Thank you so, so much.
那么，Noam，如果大家想联系你，可以在网上哪里找到你，
Well, with that, Noam, where can people find you online if they want to reach out,
或者提些后续问题？
maybe follow up questions?
听众又能怎样帮到你呢？是的。
And how can listeners be useful to you? Yeah.
找到我最好的地方是在 LinkedIn 上。
So the best places to find me are on LinkedIn.
我很乐意和任何想在 LinkedIn 或 Lenny's community 里联系我的人交流。
I'd love to connect with anyone who wants to connect on LinkedIn or within Lenny's community.
在你的 Slack 里。
Within your stack.
我常在那里活动，也总是很乐意和社区里的人聊天。
I hang out there and always happy to talk to people within the community.
所以请在 LinkedIn 或 Slack 上找我，那样最好。
So please catch me on LinkedIn or on Slack. That would be best.
Noam，如果你在看这个，听众能怎样帮到你？
How can listeners be useful to you, Noam, if you're watching this?
我想传达的是，希望这项研究对你有所帮助。
What I would like to convey is that I hope this research has been helpful to you.
而最重要的是，我希望你能考虑参与我们未来的研究
And more than anything, I hope that you consider participating in future research
项目。
projects of ours.
我真的非常高兴我们能做这些事，Lenny，还有。
I'm really, really glad that we get to do these things, Lenny and. And.
我想给所有正在观看的你一个机会，去更多了解科技领域正在
I want to give all of you watching the opportunity to learn more about what's going
发生的事情，你如何能把工作做得更好，
on in tech, how you can be better at your job, you know,
你如何能对工作感觉更好，以及这中间的一切。
how you can feel better about your job and all things in in between.
我们计划继续进行两种调查，嗯，对社区的快速投票，
We plan to continue conducting both, um, quick polls of the community in depth,
更长篇幅的深度调查、访谈，各种各样的形式。
longer form surveys, interviews, all sorts of things.
所以如果你收到一条消息、一封邮件，
And so if you get a message, an email,
或一条关于研究项目的 Slack 消息，请参与，我们很想听到你的声音，
a Slack about a research project please participate would love to hear your voices,
听到你的观点，然后把这些反馈给社区，
hear your perspectives and then share that back with the community
希望这能让我们都把工作做得更好，也对工作感觉更好。
and hopefully it makes us all better at our jobs and also feel better about our jobs.
因为我确实希望，尽管这里面很多内容有点艰难，
Because I do hope that even though much of this was a little bit tough
甚至有些消极，Lenny，我和你一样，是个永远的乐观主义者。
and perhaps negative, I, too, Lenny, am an eternal optimist.
我是一个技术乐观主义者。
I'm a techno optimist.
我相信这一切正朝着好的方向发展，我想确保我们能
I believe this is going in good directions and I want to make sure we capture
准确地把它记录下来。
that accurately.
所以，是的，请参与。我们很期待在下一个研究项目中见到你。
So yeah, please participate. We'd love to see you in our next research project.
很好的请求。
Excellent ask.
那么，Noam，非常感谢你来到这里。太感谢了。
With that, Noam, thank you so much for being here. Thanks a bunch.
非常感谢大家的收听。
Thank you so much for listening.
如果你觉得有价值，可以在 Apple Podcasts、
If you found this valuable, you can subscribe to the show on Apple Podcasts,
Spotify 或你喜欢的播客应用上订阅本节目。
Spotify or your favorite podcast app.
也请考虑给我们打个分或留下评论，因为
Also, please consider giving us a rating or leaving a review as
这真的能帮助其他听众找到这档播客。
that really helps other listeners find the podcast.
你可以在 Lennyspodcast.com 上找到所有往期节目或了解更多关于本节目的信息。
You can find all past episodes or learn more about the show at Lenny's podcast.com.
我们下期再见。
See you in the next episode.